<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael Jay Lissner</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/feeds/backpacking.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://michaeljaylissner.com/</id><updated>2013-11-27T10:19:46-08:00</updated><entry><title>Our New Zealand Blog</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2013/11/27/our-new-zealand-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-11-27T10:19:46-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2013-11-27:posts/2013/11/27/our-new-zealand-blog/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you seek our blog about our journey on the Te Araroa trail, it lies down 
&lt;a href="http://trampnewzealand.wordpress.com/"&gt;this path&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="te araroa"></category><category term="new zealand"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="Z"></category></entry><entry><title>Snow Mountain Distance Map</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2013/08/27/snow-mountain-distance-map/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-27T10:48:25-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2013-08-27:posts/2013/08/27/snow-mountain-distance-map/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I put on my cartographer&amp;#8217;s hat today and made a distance map 
(&lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/archive/distance-map.png"&gt;png&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/archive/distance-map.svg"&gt;svg&lt;/a&gt;) for Snow Mountain. The regular map for this area doesn&amp;#8217;t 
have any distance markers 
on it, so these are based on talking with the ranger in the park. He seemed
knowledgeable, so these numbers are probably the best we&amp;#8217;ll get for a&amp;nbsp;while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="map" src="https://michaeljaylissner.com/archive/distance-map.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If somebody discovers that the rangers in Snow Mountain finally have firm 
distances, let me know what they are, and I&amp;#8217;ll happily update this map. 
Until then, attached is the map as both an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SVG&lt;/span&gt; and a png.&amp;nbsp;Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="backpacking"></category><category term="snow mountain"></category><category term="maps"></category><category term="cartography"></category></entry><entry><title>Best Energy Pack for Ultra-light, Long-Distance Backpacking</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2013/07/19/battery-packs-for-ultralight-long-distance-backpacking/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-19T14:13:25-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2013-07-19:posts/2013/07/19/battery-packs-for-ultralight-long-distance-backpacking/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the best ultalight battery pack is &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; battery pack, 
but on our trip we&amp;#8217;re going to be bringing a phone, a camera, 
an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MP3&lt;/span&gt; player and two headlamps. The phone doubles as our &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; and the 
headlamps might be &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; rechargeable. Having spare energy to get us through 
longer sections is&amp;nbsp;important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve completed &lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/archive/battery-research.xlsx"&gt;some research&lt;/a&gt;, investigating which are the best 
options. As I
was reviewing the many battery pack and solar charger solutions that are 
out there, I came to a few conclusions right off the&amp;nbsp;bat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The models with turbines, like the &lt;a href="http://www.shopetoncorp.com/detail/ETO+NBOTU2000+RED"&gt;Eton BoostTurbine2000&lt;/a&gt; are crap. I
  called Eton to ask them how many cranks it would take to charge a phone. The technical support guy&amp;#8217;s response: &amp;#8220;You&amp;#8217;d be at it all day. These are meant for emergency use only.&amp;#8221; So turbines are&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The idea of using a solar panel is great, but doing so will suck. I 
 looked far and wide for an ultralight solar panel, but they&amp;#8217;re all heavier than just getting a battery pack. The problem with solar panels is that they need to have their own battery packs, so you end up carrying the extra battery pack &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; the panel itself. If you&amp;#8217;re out for really long trips, these are probably worth it, but for trips where you&amp;#8217;ll be in and out of towns, there are lighter&amp;nbsp;options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a million wannabe battery pack manufacturers, like Timetec, 
 Powergen, Rokit and Unu. They&amp;#8217;re strong on branding, but when you go to their 
 website &amp;mdash; if they have one &amp;mdash; you&amp;#8217;ll find more marketing but not
  much real innovation or information. For example, in my attached chart, 
  there are many blank spots and questions marks for these&amp;nbsp;brands. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking for battery packs for backpackers means finding one that&amp;#8217;s light, 
durable and efficient. There are a few features you probably want in&amp;nbsp;particular: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want a battery pack that will charge your devices as quickly as they
  support. Many battery packs, particularly the small ones, 
  only provide 1 amp of output from a single &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; port. If you have a device
   that can handle more (like a tablet), it&amp;#8217;ll charge quite slowly. The 
   best ones have as much as 2.5A output, and will adapt to send the right 
   amount of power to your&amp;nbsp;device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want a battery pack that charges quickly when you plug it into the 
 wall. You don&amp;#8217;t want to get stuck in town overnight because of how slowly 
 your battery pack&amp;nbsp;charges. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want a battery pack that offers &amp;#8220;pass through charging&amp;#8221;. This allows
  you to plug the battery into the wall, and plug your device into the 
  battery &amp;#8212; simultaneously &amp;#8212; allowing you to charge both at the same time. Most battery packs don&amp;#8217;t offer&amp;nbsp;this. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, you want the most energy packed into the smallest, lightest&amp;nbsp;device. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking at all these features, there are three standout energy packs, 
the &lt;a href="http://www.myinnergie.com/productdetail.php?productid=237&amp;amp;languageid=1"&gt;Innergie PocketCell Duo&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://www.ianker.com/anker-astro-external-battery-backup-charger/product/79UN53V1-B8P56A"&gt;Anker Astro 5600&lt;/a&gt; and 
the &lt;a href="http://usa.just-mobile.com/all/gum-doubleplus.html"&gt;Just Mobile Gum++&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anker Astro ($30) is the lightest of the bunch, but it also is complex,
charges slowly when plugged in, and has a complex body. It has a 
flashlight, for what that&amp;#8217;s worth, and, at 4.2 ounces, 
has an energy density of 1333 mAh/oz. It does not appear to have 
passthrough&amp;nbsp;functionality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Just Mobile Gum++ ($90) is a very simple, lightweight and durable 
option. At 4.6 ounces, it&amp;#8217;s still very light. It has a slightly lower 
energy density from the Astro (1304 mAh/oz), but boasts an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ABS&lt;/span&gt; shell, 
the fastest charge rate when plugged in (2500 mA), and just generally looks
like a good, simple&amp;nbsp;option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally is the Innergie PocketCell Duo ($90). This is the most powerful of 
the bunch, at 6800 mAh, has the highest energy density at 1456 mAh/oz) and 
has two output ports (both at 2100 mA). Unfortunately, unlike the Gum++, 
it only chargest at 1500 mA, so it will take longer to&amp;nbsp;charge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PocketCell and Gum++ are both very new products, 
and don&amp;#8217;t have many reviews. The Anker has been around awhile and has 
decent reviews, though some upset people that aren&amp;#8217;t happy with their&amp;nbsp;products. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s my recommendation: If you need a battery pack that can charge two 
devices at the same time, get the Innergie PocketCell Duo. If not, 
get the Just Mobile Gum++. If you want to do your own analysis, 
check out the attached spreadsheet and go&amp;nbsp;wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Since Innergie does not mention whether their device supports 
pass through, I&amp;#8217;ve contacted them via their contact form and via Twitter. 
After more than two months, they&amp;#8217;ve been entirely non-responsive. There is 
another person on their Twitter stream that is complaining (loudly) that 
they never responded to a broken device complaint that he had. I can&amp;#8217;t 
recommend Innergie despite their slick device, great marketing, 
etc. Something is going wrong with that&amp;nbsp;company.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="shopping"></category><category term="new zealand"></category><category term="batteries"></category><category term="backpacking"></category></entry><entry><title>Desolation Wilderness</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2013/06/17/desolation-wilderness/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-17T11:41:40-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2013-06-17:posts/2013/06/17/desolation-wilderness/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Z and I went to Desolation Wilderness this weekend in preparation for our thru hike of the Te Araroa trail in November. It was a great trip, and photos &lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/102845149340395808422/posts/ceSu99xpXe3"&gt;are here&lt;/a&gt;. If you need permission to see them, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-route"&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our route brought us to Wrights Lake at about 10pm on Friday night. From there, we hiked up to Twin Lakes and found a spot by the south western edge. This was pretty lucky. Getting across the lake’s outlet at midnight when we got there was a pain, especially for me, since I lacked a flashlight. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, we hiked halfway to Island Lakes, then south to a east-west ridge that forms one of the edge of Mt. Price. This ridge was stupidly dangerous, hoping from bounder to boulder with no safety net and a giant fall below. In wet or snowy conditions, it’d be impossible, but with some patience we were able to do it without too much trouble. Once traversed the ridge to the east, walking up the southern side of Mt. Price was a cake walk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending some time at the top, where we observed some friendly (but skinny) marmots, we headed east towards Mosquito Pass. Getting down from the top was a hairy mess, with lots of rocky cliffs we had to very carefully pick our way down. Eventually, we made it off the cliffs and into the snow fields, which happily were soft enough to glissade down. We didn’t have ice axes, so if we couldn’t glissade, we would have had to wait for the sun to get higher and melt more snow. The snow here was full of medium-sized sun cups, which Z naturally (and quite properly, given her running shoes) slid around on and hated. I hated them too, but my shoes at least afforded me some traction on them. The snow went down almost to the top of the ridge between Clyd and Aloha lakes, but not quite, and once we got there, we clamored over the rocks for a while until arriving back on trail at Mosquito Pass. From here, we walked along Lake Aloha, to camp at the southern edge.  Mozzies were pretty bad here, but bearable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, we woke up, hiked back over Mosquito Pass, and beyond it through a long valley, up and over Rockbound Pass. From there we hiked down, back into the Mosquito zone, and beyond to our the car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="regrets"&gt;Regrets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I forgot to put new batteries in my flashlight, and the old ones were all but dead. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The deet that we brought was old and didn’t seem to work too well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Z needs real shoes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ice axes would have been safer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="awesome-things"&gt;Awesome things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lake Aloha is amazing but crowded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The snow was just right, despite it being &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WAY&lt;/span&gt; too early for a trip to the High Sierras. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My legs again were abused: Scratches from the night hike with no flashlight, and sunburns from poor sunscreen application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The itinerary pushed our muscles without injury (unlike last time).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Z is a natural backpacker and a great hiking partner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="backpacking"></category><category term="desolation wilderness"></category><category term="Z"></category><category term="camping"></category></entry><entry><title>The Contents of My First Aid Kit</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/07/17/the-contents-of-my-first-aid-kit/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-07-17T21:15:02-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-07-17:posts/2009/07/17/the-contents-of-my-first-aid-kit/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I present to you approximately a decade&amp;#8217;s worth of first aid kit refinement.
Emphasis is on completeness and lightness. Inside a custom silnylon 
envelope (with no zippers or fasteners that might slow down frostbitten, 
missing or otherwise failing hands), I have the&amp;nbsp;following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An ultra-fine tipped 0.5ml&amp;nbsp;syringe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 1ml glass vial of&amp;nbsp;epinephren&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One half sheet moleskin and a small quantity of mole&amp;nbsp;foam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ten butterfly adhesive&amp;nbsp;bandages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One package&amp;nbsp;steri-strips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two 2&amp;#8221; x 3&amp;#8221; non-adhesive&amp;nbsp;pads&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some gauze, but not&amp;nbsp;much&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A package of second&amp;nbsp;skin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two single-use eye&amp;nbsp;droppers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two stainless steel safety pins (one big, one&amp;nbsp;small)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A small quantity of triple antibiotic&amp;nbsp;ointment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One nitrile&amp;nbsp;glove&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A miniature backup chapstick with&amp;nbsp;sunscreen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A single course of&amp;nbsp;ciproplaxen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thirteen 500mg Vicodin&amp;nbsp;pills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eleven 600mg ibuprofen&amp;nbsp;pills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seven 120mg pseudoephedrine hydrocloride (Sudafed)&amp;nbsp;pills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six diphenhydramine hydrochloride (Benadryl)&amp;nbsp;pills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dosage and indication instructions for all of the above&amp;nbsp;pills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/archive/SOAPA_Note.xls"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SOAP&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;note&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total weight is 124.7 grams (4.4 oz.). Don&amp;#8217;t take this as medical&amp;nbsp;advice. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="backpacking"></category><category term="first aid"></category><category term="gear"></category></entry><entry><title>Snow Camping in Sequoia</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/02/20/snow-camping-in-sequoia/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-02-20T19:25:01-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-02-20:posts/2009/02/20/snow-camping-in-sequoia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went snow camping with some friends in Sequoia National Park last weekend, 
and had a blast as always. We built a quinzhee and went snow shoeing and cross 
country skiing. The pictures are online if you are interested in seeing them, 
and per my custom, I brought along a couple of iButtons so that we could 
record our temperature the entire&amp;nbsp;time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set them up to record the temperature every five minutes to an accuracy of 
0.1 degree Celsius. I just got a chance to work with &lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/archive/sequoia-temps.xls"&gt;the data&lt;/a&gt; a bit and I 
threw together a quick chart. The data are attached, if anybody is interested, 
but the chart really tells the story better than the 2,400 data points&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/images/Labeled Temperatures2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="iButton Temperatures" src="https://michaeljaylissner.com/images/Labeled Temperatures2.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/images/Labeled Temperatures2.png"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Click for full-size&amp;nbsp;view&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="camping"></category><category term="vacations"></category><category term="snow"></category></entry><entry><title>Went Solo Backpacking this Weekend</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/02/24/went-solo-backpacking-this-weekend/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-02-24T22:07:32-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-02-24:posts/2008/02/24/went-solo-backpacking-this-weekend/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went solo backpacking this weekend for the first time in a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LONG&lt;/span&gt; time. I think the last time I really did a trip like this one was actually before I did the &lt;a href="http://www.pcta.org"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PCT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was back in&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8216;04. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went out to Point Reyes National Park, leaving Friday after work, and returning Sunday. On Friday, I camped at the ranger station, and on Saturday, I set out on an ambitious trek covering 25 miles that day, and 5 the next. I had packed extremely lightly with no water filtration, no stove, pot, spoon. Really, the only things in my pack were food, clothes, a tarp and stakes, some knick knacks and a water&amp;nbsp;bladder. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the light load, things were going well on Saturday morning, but then, a little after lunch, it started to rain. Then pour. Then the winds came on. All in all, as it should turn out, this was &lt;a href="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/n/a/2008/02/22/state/n105157S77.DTL&amp;hw=rain&amp;sn=024&amp;sc=254"&gt;one hell of a storm&lt;/a&gt;. I set up my day so that I do a loop starting on the east heading south, and then I would hook west and head north along the coast. This meant that once the storm hit, I would be heading north on an incredibly exposed trail for about 15&amp;nbsp;miles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you folks, it was an adventure. I was so exposed that I felt like I could not stop to eat, drink or anything, so I just kept hiking for the entire distance, until I reached camp, after a long, long day. At one point, in one of the windier areas, I was running downhill, the wind coming on so hard that I began to be detached from the earth. It was actually lifting me off the ground&amp;#8230;not a lot, just a little, but enough to be a&amp;nbsp;worry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, despite the adventure, the trip was good. It gave me some time to reflect on all the changes coming on in my life, and to get out and feel&amp;nbsp;alive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did I find the answer to my question of Cal vs. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UW&lt;/span&gt;? No&amp;#8230;not in nature I&amp;nbsp;didn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hiking"></category><category term="me"></category></entry><entry><title>PCT Data Project - DONE</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/12/12/pct-temperature-project-done/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-12-12T21:29:57-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-12-12:posts/2007/12/12/pct-temperature-project-done/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m happy to announce that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PCT&lt;/span&gt; data project is&amp;nbsp;complete! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past several weeks/months, I have been slaving away over my 
computer writing this program. When used, it will generate a dynamic 
graphing area that will load up temperature data for one to six &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PCT&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;hikers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All those that are interested in the most complicated programming 
assignment I have ever worked on &lt;a href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/pct-temperatures"&gt;are welcome to check it out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am officially a free man once again! Thanks to all who made this possible
with their encouragement and&amp;nbsp;patience! &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pct"></category><category term="java"></category><category term="programming"></category><category term="project"></category></entry><entry><title>The Great Temperature Data Project</title><link href="https://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/01/great-temperature-data-project/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-11-01T20:40:55-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-11-01:posts/2007/11/01/great-temperature-data-project/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in &amp;#8216;05 when I hiked from Mexico to Canada on the Pacific Crest Trail, I 
carried a little device called an &lt;a href="http://www.iButton.com"&gt;iButton&lt;/a&gt;. 
This little device contains essentially three things: a clock, a bit of memory 
and a thermometer. It&amp;#8217;s waterproof, accurate to 0.1 degree Celsius, and is about 
the size of five dimes stacked one upon another. There are a bunch of silly 
things you can do with these, but what I chose to do with mine was to have it 
record the temperature every hour on the hour for the entire time I was hiking, 
with the idea being to get some good data about the temperature out there on 
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PCT&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, you can figure that the temperature was recorded 24 times a day 
for about 150 days, for an astounding 3600 data points, and about 150 
oscillations from the daytime high to the nighttime low. I&amp;#8217;ve spent some time 
working with the data, and it&amp;#8217;s pretty much impossible to make much use of&amp;#8230;.unless 
you write a program to interpret it. You can 
&lt;a href="http://charityhikers.org/pct/temps.htm"&gt;see it for 
yourself&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as fate should have it, I am currently enrolled in a Java programming 
class, and I have the option of doing a final project of my own choosing. 
Having not put this data to good use has been a burden on my soul for a 
couple of years now, and I&amp;#8217;ve decided to make my final project an applet that 
will allow a user to plot this data on a graph for any date range and any time 
range that they choose (e.g. 5pm to 10pm for September 20th to&amp;nbsp;23rd).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, I will attempt to post it here, but here&amp;#8217;s the question to 
you dear reader, do you have any suggestions as to features that you would be 
interested in seeing in an applet of this sort?&amp;nbsp;Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m quite excited about getting this info out there.&amp;nbsp;Finally.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pct"></category><category term="java"></category><category term="programming"></category><category term="project"></category></entry></feed>