<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael Jay Lissner</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/feeds/design.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/</id><updated>2009-05-07T20:42:13+02:00</updated><entry><title>Final Project from Interface Aesthetics Class</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/05/07/final-project-from-interface-aesthetics/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-05-07T20:42:13+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2009-05-07:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/05/07/final-project-from-interface-aesthetics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had my last day of actual class today, and the semester is really 
beginning to wind down. I still have at least 60 pages of writing to do in 
the next two weeks, but somehow it will get done. One class that I 
&lt;i&gt;have&lt;/i&gt; finished my final project work for is &lt;a href="http://courses.ischool.berkeley.edu/i290-20/s09/"&gt;Interface 
Aesthetics&lt;/a&gt;, which was a survey class covering typography, color, 
layout, web design, and a handful of other topics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the final project, we each made &lt;a href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/archive/interface-aesthetics.ppt"&gt;presentations of our work from the 
semester&lt;/a&gt;, and on Monday from 4:10 to 6pm we will be 
holding an &lt;a href="http://www.ischool.berkeley.edu/newsandevents/events/20090511exhibition"&gt;open house&lt;/a&gt; to share our work at the iSchool. A lot of it
 is really quite good, though this presentation is what I will be showing, 
 so this is one cat that's out of the bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the work in the attached could still use some refinement, 
but I will point you towards the ones titled "Type I," "Type II," 
and "Icons," which I think came out pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="project"></category><category term="interface aesthetics"></category></entry><entry><title>Dear God, This is a Terrible Interface</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/12/13/this-is-a-terrible-interface/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-12-13T19:17:04+01:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2008-12-13:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/12/13/this-is-a-terrible-interface/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The UI for a KDE Python IDE is about the worst I have ever seen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="/images/clutter.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's about 90 buttons.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="UI"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="Eric"></category></entry><entry><title>Ubuntu Disk Usage Analyzer</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/07/27/ubuntu-disk-usage-analyzer/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-07-27T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2008-07-27:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/07/27/ubuntu-disk-usage-analyzer/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No Alt" src="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/images/disk_usage-pic.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite utilities lately is the Disk Usage Analyzer that comes 
installed on Ubuntu. It can be run either locally or remotely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's pretty awesome. I have been playing with my backups lately, 
and this utility allows me not only to see which directories are large, 
but also where my files are taking up the most space. For example, 
the picture at right depicts my home directory. By mousing over the slices 
of the pie, you can see what's in them, and how big they are. By clicking on
a slice, it becomes the center of the pie, and you can see which directories
are within it (and how big they are). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of UI, I have to say this one works very well for me. I have yet to
see another app for this purpose anywhere else, though admittedly I have 
not been looking that hard.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Linux"></category><category term="storage"></category></entry><entry><title>The Prettiest Ratio and Google</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/30/the-prettiest-ratio-and-google/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-11-30T16:43:36+01:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2007-11-30:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/30/the-prettiest-ratio-and-google/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="/images/ParthenonGoldenRatio.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you haven't heard about this before, the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_ratio#Relationship_to_Fibonacci_sequence"&gt;Golden Ratio&lt;/a&gt; is the 
concept of how to define the most aesthetically pleasing ratio between two 
lengths, and can be found pretty much everywhere dating back all the way to
the Egyptian Pyramids of Giza. Examples abound in the world around us. 
Books, tables, laptops, screen sizes. Essentially anything that looks like
a well-proportioned rectangle probably fits pretty closely into the 
Golden Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can kind of see what I mean by looking at the picture of the Parthenon 
at right that I found on Wikipedia. The idea is this: The length of the 
smaller of two distances should be related in the same way to the longer of
two distances as the longer of two distances is related to the sum of the 
shorter plus the longer distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that's too confusing, perhaps this will help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="/images/Golden%20Ratio%20Formula.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still confused? How about this: The Golden Ratio is 1.61803399.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went online a few days ago to figure out how to dimension an applet that 
I was making, and discovered yet another cool Google tool. Googling for 
"400 * golden ratio" yields the search result of 647. Very cool.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="google"></category></entry></feed>