<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael Jay Lissner</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/feeds/environment.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//michaeljaylissner.com/</id><updated>2009-02-13T17:06:29-08:00</updated><entry><title>Thoreau Would Have Found This Amusing...or not</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/02/13/thoreau-would-have-found-this-amusing-or-not/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-02-13T17:06:29-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-02-13:posts/2009/02/13/thoreau-would-have-found-this-amusing-or-not/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I played around with a new site today called &lt;a href="http://wattzon.com"&gt;WattzOn.com&lt;/a&gt; that helps
you to figure out how much energy your existence consumes on a daily basis.
It's a pretty useful site because it asks pretty thorough questions, 
and then reports on you vs. historical American, you vs. the world, 
you vs. lightbulbs, etc. Here's my consumption of energy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="//michaeljaylissner.com/images/wattzon.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty cool right? Who knew that my biggest environmental damage is coming 
from government? Here's me vs. historical Americans:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="//michaeljaylissner.com/images/wattzon2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm doing pretty well relative to the average American, 
and I need to follow Thoreau's advice about not paying my taxes. Got it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="environment"></category><category term="visualizations"></category><category term="metrics"></category></entry><entry><title>Final Papers on Metrics of Sustainability Class</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/01/13/final-paper-on-metrics-of-sustainability-class/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-01-13T11:35:43-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-01-13:posts/2009/01/13/final-paper-on-metrics-of-sustainability-class/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last semester I took a class at the UC Berkeley School of Business (Haas) 
entitled &lt;em&gt;Metrics of Sustainability&lt;/em&gt;. It was an interesting class all 
in all, though frustrating at times because of the emphasis on making 
sustainability something that businesses will &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to do. Our 
professor was a jocular fellow, though his history at large companies 
became evident in his notes on our final paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//michaeljaylissner.com/pdfs/energy-metrics.pdf"&gt;The paper itself&lt;/a&gt; is designed to set up metrics for analyzing the social, 
financial, and environmental sustainability of a company in the energy 
sector. The project was at once overly simple and overly complicated. On 
the one hand, it was really quite tempting to just write metrics like, 
"Did you damage the environment during the last year?" "Did you lose 
money?" On the other hand, writing complicated, and specific metrics was 
really the name of the game, and the hard part was finding the balance 
between the two. I was quite happy with the balance that we found, 
but our feedback was that our metrics were too complicated, 
and that there were too many of them. So it goes I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, for those interested, &lt;a href="//michaeljaylissner.com/pdfs/energy-metrics.pdf"&gt;I have attached our metrics&lt;/a&gt; for the 
energy sector to this post.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sustainability"></category><category term="energy"></category><category term="paper"></category></entry><entry><title>Stop Getting Catalogs</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/07/28/stop-getting-catalogs/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-07-28T21:38:57-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-07-28:posts/2008/07/28/stop-getting-catalogs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.catalogchoice.org/badge.js?color=green"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a quick post today to promote &lt;a href="http://catalogchoice.org"&gt;Catalog Choice.org&lt;/a&gt;. I've been using it now for the past six months, and I am beginning to reap the fruit of my labors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a pretty slick site that I recommend everybody sign up for. Essentially, once you're signed up, whenever you get junk mail, you log into the site, look up the publisher, and opt out. They contact the publisher on your behalf, and you're done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've come across a couple of pieces of junk mail so far that aren't in their database, but I have suggested those items to Catalog Chioce, and they say they'll get to them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site itself is sponsored by the &lt;a href="http://ecologycenter.org"&gt;Ecology Center&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://nwf.org"&gt;National Wildlife Federation&lt;/a&gt;, so it seems legit enough. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out and take control of your junk mail.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="eco-tip"></category><category term="junk mail"></category></entry><entry><title>While Cleaning the Block</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/07/19/while-cleaning-the-block/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-07-19T15:27:04-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-07-19:posts/2008/07/19/while-cleaning-the-block/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spent a couple hours cleaning my block today. Among the very special trash I picked up, I found not one, not two, but two and a half used hypodermic needles. Also of interest, one of my neighbors seems to have placed a box of 100 fresh, sterile needles outside their house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't help but wonder if that is a good way to do a needle exchange program. You throw it on the street. I put a whole box of them outside my fence on the sidewalk. Hmmm...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the up side, picking up trash seems to be a great, high-profile way to build community. The trash around my house is so bad that I could definitely use help picking it up, and every time I or my girlfriend are out there, we seem to meet allies that want to fix up the neighborhood. I collected one guy's info today, and she collected somebody else's info last week. If we keep this up, we may build a nice set of contacts of all our neighbors. So that's how meeting your neighbors works. Huh.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="berkeley"></category></entry><entry><title>Fiji Water Tries, Fails to Be Smart</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/06/03/fiji-tries-fails-to-be-smart/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-06-03T18:54:03-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-06-03:posts/2008/06/03/fiji-tries-fails-to-be-smart/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it seems somebody is reading my blog after all. After reading &lt;a href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/05/15/meet-my-enemy/"&gt;my post
regarding my hate of Fiji water&lt;/a&gt;, Fiji has responded by &lt;a href="http://www.fijigreen.com"&gt;creating a new 
website&lt;/a&gt; that tries to lure consumers out of their minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's great that Fiji Water wants to lower their carbon impact, 
but come on folks. Talk about green-washing. This is just stupid. If you 
care about the environment, stop bottling water in Fiji. Actually, 
just stop bottling water. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="environment"></category><category term="water"></category></entry><entry><title>Eco-tip 5 - Stop Junk Mail</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/05/04/stop-junk-mail/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-05-04T20:41:05-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-05-04:posts/2008/05/04/stop-junk-mail/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to stop junk mail in three steps, as gleaned from &lt;a href="http://www.recycleworks.org"&gt;recycleworks.org&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Hit the big dogs first&lt;/strong&gt;
Write two letters. One to: Harte Hanks Direct Mailing, Circulation, c/o Pennysaver, 2830 Orbiter St., Brea, CA 92821. The other to: Valassis Direct Mail, Inc., Consumer Assistance, PO Box 249, Windsor, CT 06095. On each, ask for your name to be removed from their mailing list, and make sure to give them all variations on your name (Beth, Elizabeth, Betsy, etc). For template letters, click &lt;a href="http://www.stopjunkmail.org/sample/dma.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.stopjunkmail.org/sample/advo.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Hit the medium dogs next&lt;/strong&gt;
Contact Direct Marketing Association (DMA), and get off their list. &lt;a href="https://www.dmachoice.org/MPS/proto1_reg.php"&gt;Online seems easiest,&lt;/a&gt; though it requires a credit card to "confirm your identity".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opt out of credit card offers by calling the opt out number: 1-888-567-8688. This, I believe requires your Social Security Number, but I assure you it's legit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opt out of Publisher's Clearinghouse by calling 1-800-645-9242.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opt out of shopping flyers:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;ValPak Coupons: 800-237-6266.
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Advo/Valassis: 888-241-6760, or online at &lt;a href="http://www.advo.com/consumersupport.html"&gt;www.advo.com/consumersupport.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Get catalogs gone&lt;/strong&gt;
You can opt out of some catalogs by going to &lt;a href="http://catalogchoice.org"&gt; catalogchoice.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="eco-tip"></category></entry><entry><title>Eco-tip 4 - Hibernate vs. Suspend</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/12/07/eco-tip-4-hibernate-vs-suspend/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-12-07T18:22:49-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-12-07:posts/2007/12/07/eco-tip-4-hibernate-vs-suspend/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For some reason, this bit of knowledge just hasn't gotten out there to the masses. I guess it's a bit nerdy, but here goes. When computers are not in use, they can do two very different things. They can either suspend, or they can hibernate (or you can turn them off of course). When they suspend, they go into a power saving mode that stores the state of your computer in RAM. When they are hibernating, the state of your computer is stored on the hard drive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important distinction because RAM requires energy to store information (making it volatile memory), and your hard drive does not (making it non-volatile memory). Hence, any time your computer is in suspend mode, it is incurring a negative environmental impact, and any time it is hibernating, it is incurring no more impact than a lump of silicon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. I won't get into how to deal with these in GNU+Linux, (because I can't get my laptop to do either), but &lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windowsxp/using/mobility/getstarted/hibernate.mspx"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; has some good information on how to do it in XP. If you are a Mac owner, this decision has been made for you. Your computer will suspend and hibernate at the same time, and there is no easy way I know of to hibernate only. (They call this SafeSleep, and the idea is that if the RAM hasn't been reset by a loss of power, it will boot from RAM. Otherwise, it will boot from the hard drive.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also mention that hibernation is a great alternative to leaving your computer on when you go home at the end of the day. It saves the state exactly how you left the computer, and saves the environment by not using energy through the night.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="eco-tip"></category><category term="computer"></category></entry><entry><title>Eco-Tip 3 - Buy Locally, Buy Seasonally</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/19/eco-tip-3-buy-locally-buy-seasonally/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-11-19T20:42:03-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-11-19:posts/2007/11/19/eco-tip-3-buy-locally-buy-seasonally/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's taking some time to catch on, but this is another something to think about when you're out shopping: If you live in LA, and it comes to a choice between local oranges, Mexico oranges and oranges from Florida, choose local. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only does it save you money (theoretically), it's fresher and it's better for the environment. Because it was grown locally, it didn't have to travel, and thus didn't pollute its way all the way from the other side of the world. Because it is more likely to have come off the tree more recently, it didn't have to be refrigerated for the past day/week/month, and is also fresher and more delicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, naturally (no pun intended), this works better for some areas of the country than others, and for some foods better than others. Walnuts for example are almost exclusively grown in California; pineapples and sugar from Hawai'i. So this brings us to another aspect of the food buying game: switch to foods that are local, like honey as opposed to sugar, and avoid those that come from distant places, like Hawai'i.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final piece of this tip is to buy seasonally. Not only will the food taste better, but it won't have been in the freezer for the past six months, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best thing to do, if you have the ability to do so is, of course, to plant some seeds and grow your own.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="eco-tip"></category></entry><entry><title>Eco-Tip 2 - Think Long Term...Really Long Term.</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/06/eco-tip-2-think-long-term-really-long-term/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-11-06T20:21:34-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-11-06:posts/2007/11/06/eco-tip-2-think-long-term-really-long-term/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="//michaeljaylissner.com/images/longnowclock.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, somehow two weeks have already gone past, and it's time for another 
eco-tip. This week is going to be an easy one for me because on Sunday I saw
 a truly beautiful concept: truly long-term thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of pure chance, I ended up at the &lt;a href="http://www.longnow.org" 
target="_blank"&gt;Long Now Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Fort Mason, where I saw a prototype 
for a clock that will use solar power to run for approximately 10,
000 years. The idea was beautiful because it really blows the top off of 
most environmental thinking these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much talk is given to global warming, that it seems like we're forgetting
 the whole point of the environmental movement. The point is 
 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that the world is getting warmer, 
 or even that the climate is changing. The point &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; 
 that if the climate changes very much, we'll probably all die. It's like 
 the joke about having a fear of heights: It's not that you're afraid of 
 being up high - it's that you're scared that if you fall, 
 you'll hit the ground and die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I digress. As I was saying, the Long Now clock is a clock that will 
synchronize (and probably charge) itself with the sun every day for a very 
long time. Obviously, the idea is not to track the time from now until 12,
007CE. The idea is to try to imagine what it would take for us to live that 
long. It kind of looks like we might annihilate ourselves before this clock 
ticks its last tick, but it's somehow nice to know that if we do something 
that foolish, at least this clock will sit there happily ticking without us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I invite you to check out &lt;a href="http://www.longnow.org" 
target="_blank"&gt;their site&lt;/a&gt; (which is awesome), and to imagine where we 
might be in 10,000 years. I predict that ultimately we won't be here (but 
at least the clock will).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="eco-tip"></category></entry><entry><title>The Plan: One Environmental Tip Every Other Week</title><link href="//michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/10/24/eco-tip-1-the-plan-one-environmental-tip-every-other-week/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-10-24T22:30:12-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-10-24:posts/2007/10/24/eco-tip-1-the-plan-one-environmental-tip-every-other-week/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people have been saying to me, "Dude, what's with the green blog...why's it so...ummm...green?" Well, there's a reason for this my friends. The reason is that I had to choose a color, and I went with green to go with my profound love of our friend Gaea. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along those lines, in thinking about things to post that might be interesting, I came up with a theory that if I put my mind to it, (and you, the public chips in, hint, hint) I (we) can come up with an environmental tip that is worth posting every two weeks or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might not work out, then again it might. We'll see, it all depends on whether I (we) can come up with things to write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to kick it off, I shall follow on the wisdom of my elders, and post the thing that I have been told is the MOST important thing to do to cut down YOUR carbon footprint: Insulate your house. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I understand, it's really just that simple. If you want to make the biggest dollar/CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; reduction possible, make your house a fortress of insulation. No drafts equals less heater and less air-conditioner. And, since in 2006 59% of non-petroleum U.S. energy came from coal&amp;sup1;, this is a very real way to cut down your impact. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan this winter is to cover the windows with Cyran wrap, and see if I can get it to tighten up by hitting it with a blow dryer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;sup1; &lt;small&gt;Source: &lt;a href="http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/aer/pdf/pages/sec1_8.pdf"&gt;http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/aer/pdf/pages/sec1_8.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="eco-tip"></category></entry></feed>