<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael Jay Lissner</title><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/feeds/music.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>://michaeljaylissner.com/</id><updated>2008-11-11T00:50:41-08:00</updated><entry><title>Our Poor Great Grandparents</title><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/11/11/our-poor-great-grandparents/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-11-11T00:50:41-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:,2008-11-11:://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/11/11/our-poor-great-grandparents/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's important to have perspective these days. Times are changing, you know, and it can be hard to keep track of how things used to be. In that vein, I found an interesting quote from 1978:&lt;blockquote&gt;Children who begin school today have probably listened to more music than their great grandparents heard in their entire lives.&lt;/blockquote&gt;It's pretty hard to imagine music as such a treat, since I listen to it pretty much every day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also reminds me of the Stravinky's &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rite_of_Spring"&gt;Rite of Spring&lt;/a&gt;, which was so raucous that it caused riots. These days people get offended by rap, punk and video games (oh my!), and claim that they make children into little ne'er-do-wells. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Riots though? I can't imagine music causing riots ever again.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="perspective"></category></entry><entry><title>Music Stats</title><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/10/08/music-stats/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-10-08T14:35:46-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:,2008-10-08:://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/10/08/music-stats/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have this problem when I am listening to music that I almost never choose artists whose name starts with anything after the letter D. When I am browsing for music, I just never get that far in the list. For some time, I've wondered if this is my fault, or if I just have more music in the front of my collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time came to do a little stats work and figure out why this is. Here are the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a strong predominance of the letters A-E, there is also one in the P-T range. This leads me to believe that I should hunt for music in that area more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No Alt" src="://michaeljaylissner.com/images/Number of Occurances Pentads-img1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I expected A-E to come out ahead, who would have thought that B would have more than 80 artists, almost twice the second most common letter? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No Alt" src="://michaeljaylissner.com/images/Number of Occurances Pentads-img2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what conclusions does this lead to? One: That I need to look at my music beyond the letter D. Two: That B is a very popular letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those wondering about their own music collection, if you browse to your music folder and run the following, it will tell you how many artists starting with that letter you have. For the example below, it tells me I have 30 artists with the letter 'A'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ls&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Music&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;grep&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="statistics"></category><category term="visualizations"></category></entry><entry><title>Happy Mother's Day, Decemberists Style</title><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/05/11/happy-mothers-day/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-05-11T11:56:38-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:,2008-05-11:://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/05/11/happy-mothers-day/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="a-cautionary-song"&gt;A Cautionary Song&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a place your mother goes when everybody else is soundly sleeping.
Through the lights of beacon street and if you listen you can hear her weeping, she's weeping, 
Cause the gentlemen are calling and the snow is softly falling on her petticoats,
And she's standing in the harbor and she's waiting for the sailors in the jolly boat. See how they approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With dirty hands and trousers torn they grapple 'til she's safe within 
their keeping.
A gag is placed between her lips to keep her sorry tongue from any speaking, or screaming.
And they row her out to packets where the sailor's sorry racket calls for maidenhead.
And she's scarce above the gunnels when her clothes fall to a bundle and she's laid in bed on the upper deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so she goes from ship to ship, her ankles clasped her arms so rudely 
pinioned
'till at last she's satisfied the lot of the marina's teeming minions, in their opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they tell her not to say a thing to cousin, kindred, 
kith or kin or she'll end up dead.
And they throw her thirty dollars and return her to the harbor where she goes to bed.
And this is how you're fed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So be kind to your mother, though she may seem an awful bother, 
and the next time she tries to feed you collard greens, remember what she does when you're asleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="mom"></category></entry><entry><title>Personal Music Collections</title><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/02/02/personal-music-collections/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-02-02T20:02:59-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:,2008-02-02:://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/02/02/personal-music-collections/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was curious which artists of mine had the most songs, so I ran:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;du Music/ | sort -nr | head -11
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we know that my top ten artists are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;% du Music/ | sort -nr | head -11
17582796        Music/
490928  Music/Radiohead
378148  Music/Daft Punk
315856  Music/Red Hot Chili Peppers
313032  Music/Massive Attack
306228  Music/Kanye West
305796  Music/Outkast
289288  Music/Nirvana
276416  Music/Beck
258544  Music/Nine Inch Nails
248608  Music/Beatles, The
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Linux"></category><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>Black Sabbath - Children of the Grave</title><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/12/30/black-sabbath-children-of-the-grave/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-12-30T12:28:27-08:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:,2007-12-30:://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/12/30/black-sabbath-children-of-the-grave/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Revolution in their minds 
The children start to march
Against the world in which they have to live 
And the hate that's in their hearts 
They're tired of being pushed around and told just what to do 
They'll fight the world until they've won and love comes flowing through&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children of tomorrow live in the tears that fall today 
Will the sun rise up tomorrow bringing peace in any way?
Must the world live in the shadow of atomic fear? 
Can they win the fight for peace or will they disappear? Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you children of the world listen to what I say 
If you want a better place to live in spread the word today
Show the world that love is still alive you must be brave 
Or you children of today are children of the grave yeah!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>I want ogg on my iPod</title><link href="://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/09/16/ogg-on-ipod/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-09-16T19:59:23-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:,2007-09-16:://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/09/16/ogg-on-ipod/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
I know this post is going to alienate just about everybody that would ever consider reading my blog, but here's the deal: I want all iPods to support the ogg file format. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the uninitiated, the ogg format is like the MP3 or the AAC format, except for a couple of very important differences. One, it's free, which is to say that it doesn't belong to some company, and every time I use it I'm not supposed to be giving them a nickel or something. (The MP3 format technically is licensed to the company that created it, so theoretically, every time you buy a computer, MP3 player, etc., you're supposed to give them some quantity of money.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other reason that I am hereby requesting ogg on my iPod  is because it's better. It sounds better. It compresses better. Are there other metrics that we should be using? None that I know of. I want ogg. Steve Jobs, do you hear me now?! 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, the theoretical argument above holds water, but I have personal reasons for this desire: I have 357 ogg files that I can't listen to on my iPod! This pretty much gives me three choices: One, install &lt;a href="http://www.rockbox.org/" title="Rockbox.org"&gt;Rockbox&lt;/a&gt; on my iPod (I have, it didn't work reliably). Two, convert the ogg files to MP3s (this solution would create inferior-quality songs). Or, three, only listen to those songs on my computer (also a lame solution). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I should also mention while I am on this rant that I have flac files as well. Why doesn't the iPod support those! iPods are great, but these are serious shortcomings.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="copyright"></category><category term="ipod"></category></entry></feed>