<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael Jay Lissner</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/feeds/policy-law-politics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://michaeljaylissner.com/</id><updated>2014-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Creating a Non-Profit</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2014/10/14/becoming-a-non-profit/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2014-10-14:posts/2014/10/14/becoming-a-non-profit/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="the-goal"&gt;The Goal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is an attempt to document the things that we’ve done at &lt;a href="http://www.freelawproject.org"&gt;Free Law Project&lt;/a&gt; to get our official Federal and State non-profit status. This has been a grueling process for Brian and me but as we announced on Twitter, we now have it officially in hand, and likely in record time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn't tax advice, but we're happy to announce the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; approved our 501(c)(3) app, so donations are deductible! &lt;a href="https://t.co/UjaBgSJorr"&gt;https://t.co/UjaBgSJorr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Free Law Project (@FreeLawProject) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/FreeLawProject/status/520620527963369472"&gt;October 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href="http://freelawproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/006-non-profit-status-letter-redacted.pdf"&gt;this beauty&lt;/a&gt;! We’re finally the real deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All through the process, I wished there was something that had all the documentation of the process, so this is my attempt at such a post. I’m writing this after the fact, so I expect that I’ll munge a few details. If you catch me making a mistake, you can either &lt;a href="https://github.com/mlissner/michaeljaylissner.com/edit/master/content/on-memory.md"&gt;edit this page&lt;/a&gt; yourself using &lt;a href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2014/10/06/editing-on-github-a-non-technical-explainer/"&gt;my handy guide&lt;/a&gt;, or you can &lt;a href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/contact"&gt;send me a note&lt;/a&gt; and I’ll update it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="before-we-begin"&gt;Before We Begin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three notes before we begin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our complete &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; packet &lt;a href="http://owncloud.freelawproject.org/public.php?service=files&amp;amp;t=679d702c8596346f261db57e18405afd&amp;amp;download"&gt;is available&lt;/a&gt;. Please feel free to take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very best resource we found for this was &lt;a href="http://www.publiccounsel.org/tools/assets/files/0027.pdf"&gt;a checklist&lt;/a&gt; from Public Counsel which reads like this blog post if it were written by qualified lawyers.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing here, there, or anywhere is tax advice or legal advice or advice in any way, period. This is an overview of the process as we understand it. It might work for you, it might not. We’re not tax or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; experts. Hell, I’m not even a lawyer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-overall-process"&gt;The Overall Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the major steps for California and Federal recognition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reserve the name of your organization with the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check for trademarks on your organization name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt; from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get official with the Secretary of State of California&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write Bylaws&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write Articles of Incorporation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write Conflict of Interest and Ethics Policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hold a meeting creating directors (and having them resign as incorporators, if necessary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hold a meeting to ratify and adopt everything above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File Statement of Information with Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register with the California Attorney General’s registry of charitable trusts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get Federal recognition as a 501(c)(3)&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;-1023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your organization’s press coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your homepage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Articles of Incorporation stamped by the State Secretary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phone a friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File for California tax exemption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get Municipal recognition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reserve-your-name-with-the-secretary-of-state"&gt;Reserve Your Name with the Secretary of State&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important step if you think somebody else might already have your name or if you think it might get scooped up before you finish your paperwork. This is your opportunity to say that your organization is named such-and-such and nobody else can have that name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information about this can be &lt;a href="http://www.sos.ca.gov/business/be/name-availability.htm"&gt;found on the Secretary of State’s website&lt;/a&gt;. The process involves downloading &lt;a href="http://www.sos.ca.gov/business/corp/pdf/naavreservform.pdf"&gt;a form&lt;/a&gt;, filling it out, mailing it in, and then waiting for a reply. Once you get the reply, the name is yours for 60 days. This is probably also a good time to…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="check-for-trademarks"&gt;Check for Trademarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think the name of your organization might be a trademark, you should check &lt;a href="http://tess2.uspto.gov/bin/gate.exe?f=tess&amp;amp;state=4802:wiyhnl.1.1"&gt;the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USPTO&lt;/span&gt;’s trademark database&lt;/a&gt; to see if it is. If so, it’s probably wise to re-think the name of your organization. Naming your organization the Nike Charitable Trust probably won’t work out well for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="get-an-ein"&gt;Get an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the official step that’s required to incorporate your organization and it’s a fairly easy one. Once this is done you’ll have an Employer Identification Number (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt;) from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, there is &lt;a href="http://www.irs.gov/Businesses/Small-Businesses-&amp;amp;-Self-Employed/Apply-for-an-Employer-Identification-Number-%28EIN%29-Online"&gt;a multi-step form on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;. Work your way through it, and if you come out the other side, you’ll quickly be the owner of a freshly minted &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href="http://www.taxanalysts.com/www/features.nsf/Articles/E76DFBC8665E47B185257B1D006B1656?OpenDocument"&gt;Keep it private, as you would an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="get-official-with-california"&gt;Get Official with California&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, you’ve moved past the easy stuff. It’s time for the weird and difficult paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="write-bylaws-articles-of-incorporation-and-conflict-of-interest-and-ethics-policy"&gt;Write Bylaws, Articles of Incorporation and Conflict of Interest and Ethics Policy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing these three items is a very persnickety part of the process. Each item &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; include certain phrases and failure to include those phrases will sink any attempt to get 501(c)(3) status down the road. The template we used for each of these was created by &lt;a href="http://www.publiccounsel.org"&gt;Public Counsel&lt;/a&gt; and can be downloaded from their website (&lt;a href="http://www.publiccounsel.org/publications?id=0060"&gt;Bylaws&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.publiccounsel.org/publications?id=0059"&gt;Articles of Incorporation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.publiccounsel.org/publications?id=0061"&gt;Ethics Policy&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best process we discovered for this was to very carefully work our way through each template and to update any section that needed it. The &lt;a href="http://freelawproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Articles_of_Incorporation_and_Bylaws.pdf"&gt;result&lt;/a&gt; clocks in at 25 pages for the Bylaws and Articles of Incorporation and ten pages for the  Conflict of Interest and Ethics Policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hold-some-meetings"&gt;Hold Some Meetings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, you’ve got your name, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt;, Bylaws, Articles of Incorporation and  Conflict of Interest and Ethics Policy all ready. Now what? Well, now we enter the portion of the process that involves magic and wizardry. What we do now is we hold two meetings. Feel free to chant during these meetings if that helps them make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first meeting serves the purpose of creating directors and having them resign as incorporators, if necessary. To have this meeting, get all of your incorporators and directors together and decide to make it so. Have your secretary keep minutes from the meeting. You’ll need them for the 501(c)(3). &lt;a href="http://freelawproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/003-minutes_incorporators.pdf"&gt;Here are ours&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.publiccounsel.org/tools/assets/files/mins_incorp.doc"&gt;here’s the template we used&lt;/a&gt;. You can see how this might feel a bit like voodoo magic if your board of directors is the same group of people as your incorporators (as in our case) — One minute they’re incorporators, the next they’re directors, and the people that authorized the switch are themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second meeting is where the real business goes down. Here you adopt all of the paperwork you created above, establish bank accounts, etc. Again, we used the templates from Public Counsel to keep minutes for this meeting. &lt;a href="http://freelawproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/004-mins_1st_bd_mtg-signed.pdf"&gt;Check out our minutes for details&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.publiccounsel.org/tools/assets/files/mins_1st_bd_mtg.doc"&gt;here’s a template&lt;/a&gt;. You’ll also see in our minutes a waiver of notice that waives the director’s normal requirement to tell people about the meeting in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two meetings can (and probably will) take place back to back, but they need to have &lt;em&gt;separate&lt;/em&gt; minutes and need to be &lt;em&gt;separate&lt;/em&gt; meetings. This is because until the board adopts themselves in the first meeting, they can’t very well do the things in the second meeting. Voodoo? Perhaps. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="file-statement-of-information-with-secretary-of-state-of-california"&gt;File Statement of Information with Secretary of State of California&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within 90 days of when you filed your original Articles of Incorporation, you need to take all of the above and send it into the secretary of state along with the &lt;a href="http://www.sos.ca.gov/business/corp/pdf/so/corp_so100.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SI&lt;/span&gt;-100 form&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do all of this well and properly, you’ll soon be registered with the State of California, but until you get your 501(c)(3) pushed through you can’t become an official California non-profit, so you’ll have to hold on for a bit for that piece of the puzzle. More on this in a moment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="register-with-the-california-attorney-general"&gt;Register with the California Attorney General&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing you’ve got to do, once you’ve got state recognition is to register with the California Attorney General. You have 30 days to do this from the moment when you first had assets as an organization. Be swift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, there are &lt;a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/agweb/pdfs/charities/charitable/initialReg.pdf"&gt;instructions on the Attorney General’s website&lt;/a&gt;, and there’s &lt;a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/agweb/pdfs/charities/charitable/ct1-form.pdf"&gt;a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; that you need to complete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="get-federal-recognition"&gt;Get Federal Recognition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve come this far, you’re actually doing pretty well, but it’s time to find a good fortifying drink, because it’s about to get worse. Much worse. Our operating theory is that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; makes this hard because they simply don’t like giving tax exemptions — it’s antithetical to their whole raison d’être. But be that as it may, we must persevere if we’re going to make our organization a 501(c)(3). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what’s this process look like? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there are really only two forms that you need to worry about. The first is the &lt;a href="http://www.stayexempt.irs.gov/StartingOut/InteractiveForm1023Application.aspx"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;-1023&lt;/a&gt; and the second is the &lt;a href="http://www.stayexempt.irs.gov/checklist.pdf"&gt;checklist for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;-1023&lt;/a&gt;. That should tell you something about the process you’re about to engage in: There’s a form for the form. Oh, and that’s not all: there’s a &lt;a href="http://www.stayexempt.irs.gov/StartingOut/InteractiveForm1023Application.aspx"&gt;web form&lt;/a&gt; for the form for the form. Also, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;-1023 is an &lt;em&gt;interactive&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; with parts that appear and disappear as you complete it. Also it crashes sometimes (save often!), can only be opened in Adobe Reader and there are three versions of the form and two different revisions. Dizzy yet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see if I can simplify this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;-1023 from December 2013 is currently the main form you want  — it’s long and has a lot of questions. It is available in three forms: Interactive (recommended), Regular (no interactive stuff), and Accessible (even less interactive stuff?). You only seem to be able to get this form if you answer &lt;a href="http://www.stayexempt.irs.gov/StartingOut/InteractiveForm1023Application.aspx"&gt;a bunch of questions aimed at prepping you for the process&lt;/a&gt;. Even then it gives you a zip containing the form, sigh.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 1023 checklist &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be included in your submission as a table of contents of sorts. The &lt;a href="http://www.stayexempt.irs.gov/checklist.pdf"&gt;newest one I’ve found&lt;/a&gt; is from June 2006.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are copious resources online to help you complete these forms. The ones we used were &lt;a href="http://form1023.org/"&gt;form1023.org&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://www.irs.gov/instructions/i1023/index.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;’s own documentation&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://www.irs.gov/Charities-&amp;amp;-Non-Profits/Frequently-Asked-Questions-about-Form-1023"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FAQ&lt;/span&gt; for the form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, you’ve got your forms, let’s talk a bit about the packet you’re going to send to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;. The best place to begin understanding the packet is by looking at the checklist we just downloaded. In addition to the items mentioned above, it also requests a number of new items we haven’t seen before. Most of these won’t be necessary for most non-profits, but one is new and worth mentioning: the Expedite Request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="getting-expedited"&gt;Getting Expedited&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’ve come to understand it, there are essentially three queues your paperwork can fall into at the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The urgent queue (30 days?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The normal queue (90 days?) and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The troublemaker queue (&amp;gt; 90 days / Never)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your goal is to fall into one of the first two queues. If you fall into the third, it’s possible you’ll never come out the other side. &lt;a href="http://blogs.gnome.org/jnelson/2014/06/30/the-new-501c3-and-the-future-of-free-software-in-the-united-states/"&gt;Seriously&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to fall into the first queue, you need to complete an Expedite Request. These are actually pretty straightforward, but you need to qualify. You can see an example of our Expedite Request in our &lt;a href="http://owncloud.freelawproject.org/public.php?service=files&amp;amp;t=679d702c8596346f261db57e18405afd&amp;amp;download"&gt;1023 submission&lt;/a&gt;, but basically, you need to state specific harm that will occur if your organization doesn’t get swift 501(c)(3) processing. There are &lt;a href="http://www.irs.gov/Charities-&amp;amp;-Non-Profits/Applying-for-Exemption:-Expediting-Application-Processing"&gt;guides about this on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; website&lt;/a&gt; that we used (successfully, we believe). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting faster processing is great but it’s not always possible. Failing that, the thing to do is make sure that you don’t fall into the third queue. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the important parts of this are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carefully follow &lt;a href="http://www.irs.gov/instructions/i1023/index.html"&gt;the instructions provided by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; for the 1023&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that your articles of incorporation contain the proper purpose and dissolution clauses (they will if you use the templates).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the &lt;a href="http://www.irs.gov/Charities-&amp;amp;-Non-Profits/Top-Ten-Reasons-for-Delays-in-Processing-Exempt-Organization-Applications"&gt;top ten list&lt;/a&gt; provided by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; for speeding up the process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mention any of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRS_targeting_controversy"&gt;cursed words&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;’s list to “Be On the Look Out” for (So-called &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BOLO&lt;/span&gt; words).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list is apparently no longer in use due to the furor it caused, but it’s still instructive to know what was on it. For example, in our case “Open Source” was on the list, so despite working in the open (something we believe contributes to our educational purpose), we had to be very careful never to mention that in our mission or anywhere else just to ensure there were no misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got your Expedite Request completed, it’s time to work on the 1023 itself. This is a long and arduous process that is too detailed to get into. Be careful, be thorough, follow the guides, and get help from a friend or lawyer. We found it to be incredibly useful to get somebody with experience to carefully look at our paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="other-things-we-sent-the-irs"&gt;Other Things We Sent the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the items mentioned above, we also included printed copies of a partnership agreement we have with Princeton for the hosting of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RECAP&lt;/span&gt;, a printed selection of press, and printed copies of our homepages (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RECAP&lt;/span&gt;, CourtListner, Free Law Project).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of these enclosures was mostly to keep the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; reviewer from touching their computer, but also to keep their life as simple as possible. Like any application, you want to control the information that is provided to the reviewer. Just like you wouldn’t want your next boss seeing your Facebook profile, you don’t want the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; reviewer looking up your organization’s website. There’s likely nothing bad for them to see, but you want to keep things as simple as possible. Maybe, we reason, if we provide a printed copy of our homepage they won’t bother booting up their computer. Perhaps.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="remarks-on-formatting-etc"&gt;Remarks on Formatting, Etc.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, like &lt;a href="http://www.aarongreenspan.com/writing/20130217/petitioning-rube-goldbergs-supreme-court/"&gt;filing with the Supreme Court&lt;/a&gt;, completing your 1023 involves a few formatting and clerical details that we must attend to. First you must be sure to put your name and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt; on the top of every page. This is suprisingly difficult since many of the pages are PDFs you don’t control, but you can pull it off if you try by feeding your printed documents through the printer twice. The first time, you print the regular stuff, the second time you print a blank page over and over that contains your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt; and organization name in the header. Fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing to attend to is the ordering of the documents themselves. This is the order of our 1023, and from what we can tell, you really shouldn’t do anything much different:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1023 Checklist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Request for Expedited Processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of Enclosures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 1023 itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Articles of Incorporation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bylaws&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supplemental answers to 1023 questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conflict of Interest and Ethics Policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minutes adopting Conflict of Interest and Ethics Policy (remember when we made these?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A partnership agreement we have with Princeton&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our selection of press coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Printed copies of our homepages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; Form &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SS&lt;/span&gt;-4 indicating our &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EIN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total: 83 pages of delightful paperwork and one check for $850.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="file-california-tax-exemption-forms"&gt;File California Tax Exemption Forms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, you’ll soon hear back from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt; and be granted your Federal recognition as a 501(c)(3). Congratulations on a hard-won victory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that that’s in place, it’s time to switch back to California and wrap things up with them. To do this you need to complete form 3500A (&lt;a href="https://www.ftb.ca.gov/businesses/Exempt_organizations/Applying_for_tax-exemption.shtml"&gt;information&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://www.ftb.ca.gov/forms/misc/3500a.pdf"&gt;download&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to save this form. You can’t:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Go F*** Yourself -- You cannot save this file." src="http://michaeljaylissner.com/images/cannot-save-pdf.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, fill it out, print it, and mail it in along with a copy of your Federal Recognition. If you can print to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;, that &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; save your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="get-municipal-recognition"&gt;Get Municipal Recognition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final step of this process for us, though it might come much earlier
for you, was to get in touch with the city where we incorporated and to
tell them that we exist. We tried to do this early on and had the city
staff member in charge of business licenses tell us to come back once we
had 501(c)(3) recognition. In the city we selected non-profits are
exempt from city business license fees, so that may be why they were so
lax about the timing of this paperwork. You may find in your city that
they want you to have a business license and pay related fees while
you’re waiting on 501(c)(3) status (and sometimes even after).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrapping-up"&gt;Wrapping Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, that’s the basic process of creating a non-profit and getting tax exemption from the feds, the state and your city. Most of this went pretty smoothly, but the most difficult part was by far the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRS&lt;/span&gt;-1023, and even that we were able to get our results back in about 30 days. This  feels like something of a miracle, but it took us over a year to get all the paperwork completed and submitted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end I liken the process to an incantation of a magic spell: Done correctly, you wind up with a massive pile of paperwork that magically looks like a bad-ass application for tax-exempt status that washes over anybody that looks at it, convincing him or her that your organization is charitable and deserves tax exemption in a forthright manner. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done incorrectly, you enter a hole of despair, despondency and, worse, taxation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, PDFs are &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/10548893/64911"&gt;generally compressed internally&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="IRS"></category><category term="IRS-1023"></category><category term="Non-Profit"></category><category term="CourtListener"></category><category term="Free Law Project"></category><category term="Forms"></category></entry><entry><title>In Re NSL</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2014/10/08/in-re-nsl/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2014-10-08:posts/2014/10/08/in-re-nsl/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Kurt Opsahl for EFF" src="http://michaeljaylissner.com/images/in-re-nsl/kurt.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kurt Opsahl for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EFF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the morning today in court watching &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/about/staff/kurt-opsahl"&gt;Kurt Opsahl&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org"&gt;Electronic Frontier Foundation&lt;/a&gt; deliver oral arguments for &lt;em&gt;In Re National Security Letters&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AKA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;Under Seal v. Eric Holder&lt;/em&gt;. I had originally planned on attending this as a lay person holding a smart phone camera and taking pictures, but soon after I filed &lt;a href="http://www.ca9.uscourts.gov/news_media/camera_application_form/"&gt;an application to take photos&lt;/a&gt;, I became &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; media &amp;#8220;pool&amp;#8221;, meaning I was the one guy responsible for taking photos and distributing to the press after the&amp;nbsp;fact. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I&amp;#8217;m no photographer, but since nobody else applied to take photos, here are the photos that I&amp;nbsp;took:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form method="get" target="_blank" action="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0Bwzoqmo9VXMvU0JfWldsU1Q1TUE/view?usp=sharing"&gt;
    &lt;input class="button lead" type="submit" name="download" value="Download as Zip"&gt;&lt;/input&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hereby release these as public domain photos. If you want to give me attribution, great. If not, no&amp;nbsp;worries. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="some-comments-on-nsls-and-the-proceedings"&gt;Some Comments on NSLs and the&amp;nbsp;Proceedings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The district court previously found that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_security_letter"&gt;National Security Letters (NSLs)&lt;/a&gt; violate the First Amendment and today the government appealed that finding with a variety of interesting claims. Probably my favorite was when the government claimed that the gag orders that typically apply to NSLs were necessary because without them the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FBI&lt;/span&gt; wouldn&amp;#8217;t be able to use NSLs as an investigative tool&amp;nbsp;anymore. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt Zimmerman, the attorney when this case was in the district court, put it&amp;nbsp;well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gov&amp;#39;t: &amp;quot;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FBI&lt;/span&gt; couldn&amp;#39;t function&amp;quot; if it had to review the appropriateness of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSL&lt;/span&gt; gags. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nsl?src=hash"&gt;#nsl&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wow?src=hash"&gt;#wow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Matt Zimmerman (@zim) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zim/status/519899839526490113"&gt;October 8, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing here is that it&amp;#8217;s probably true. If the gag orders were removed, the thousands of National Security Letters that the government issues each year would need more review, making it so that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FBI&lt;/span&gt; no longer had an extra-judicial backdoor into investigations. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FBI&lt;/span&gt; wouldn&amp;#8217;t want&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Judge" src="http://michaeljaylissner.com/images/in-re-nsl/judge.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a million other arguments made that I&amp;#8217;ll leave to the lawyers to discuss, but all in all it looked pretty good for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EFF&lt;/span&gt; and I think folks are feeling confident. From here, it&amp;#8217;s now up to the panel of judges to issue their decision. My bet is that regardless of what the decision says, this one will be appealed to the Supreme Court. Perhaps they&amp;#8217;ll need a photographer&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Court"></category><category term="NSL"></category><category term="EFF"></category><category term="Pictures"></category></entry><entry><title>How to help end Boy Scouts of America’s ban on gays</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2013/04/19/help-end-the-bsa-ban-on-gays/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-19T10:18:05-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2013-04-19:posts/2013/04/19/help-end-the-bsa-ban-on-gays/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 3rd, the Boy Scouts are considering lifting their ban on gays, and are putting a vote to the local and national councils. This means that it&amp;#8217;s easy to influence the vote by calling in and expressing your opinion. It&amp;#8217;s simple to do so, and more voices could change the direction of the Boy Scouts of America, allowing all boys to be included and&amp;nbsp;accepted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what to&amp;nbsp;do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scouting.org/LocalCouncilLocator.aspx"&gt;Find your local&amp;nbsp;council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give them a call or send them an email telling them your&amp;nbsp;opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact the national council via email: &lt;a href="mailto:feedback@scouting.org"&gt;feedback@scouting.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most important is to contact your local council. We need their phones to be ringing off the hook with people expressing their opinions. It truly takes no more than two minutes. Here&amp;#8217;s the San Diego council: (619) 298-6121, and the East Bay council: (925)&amp;nbsp;674-6100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you prefer a form letter, you can &lt;a href="https://secure3.convio.net/hrc/site/Advocacy?cmd=display&amp;amp;page=UserAction&amp;amp;id=1623&amp;amp;autologin=true&amp;amp;utm_term=link2&amp;amp;JServSessionIdr004=on4q7x9ly4.app304a"&gt;just do this one through the Human Rights Campaign&lt;/a&gt; (34,000 people already&amp;nbsp;have).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a simple transcript for you to&amp;nbsp;follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m [calling/wrriting] to express my desire that the Boy Scouts immediately lift their ban on gays. This ban is discriminatory, outdated and pointless. Scouting teaches many great lessons to thousands of adolescents across the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; One lesson that Scouting should not teach is that homosexuality is somehow wrong or means for&amp;nbsp;discrimination. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 3rd, I hope that you will help the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BSA&lt;/span&gt; finally makes the right decision so it can continue to lead boys into being mature and accepting&amp;nbsp;men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send this to the email above, and call your local council. This could make a&amp;nbsp;difference.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="howto"></category><category term="homosexuality"></category><category term="boy scouts"></category></entry><entry><title>Further privacy protections at CourtListener</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2012/04/27/further-privacy-protections-at-courtlistener/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-04-27T17:05:21-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2012-04-27:posts/2012/04/27/further-privacy-protections-at-courtlistener/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve &lt;a href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2012/01/16/respecting-privacy-while-providing-hundreds-of-thousands-of-public-documents/"&gt;written previously&lt;/a&gt; about the lengths we go to at CourtListener to
protect people&amp;#8217;s privacy, and today we completed one more privacy&amp;nbsp;enhancement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After my last post on this topic, we discovered that although we had 
already blocked cases from appearing in the search results of all major 
search engines, we had a privacy leak in the form of our computer-readable 
sitemaps. These sitemaps contain links to every page within a website, 
and since those links contain the names of the parties in a case, 
it&amp;#8217;s possible that a Google search for the party name could turn up results
that should be&amp;nbsp;hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was problematic, and as of now we have changed the way we serve 
sitemaps so that they use the &lt;code&gt;noindex X-Robots-Tag&lt;/code&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; header. This tells 
search crawlers that they are welcome to read our sitemaps, 
but that they should avoid serving them or indexing&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sitemaps.xml"></category><category term="privacy"></category><category term="policy"></category><category term="CourtListener"></category></entry><entry><title>The abolishment of the Emergency Court of Appeals (April 18, 1962)</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2011/08/10/the-abolishment-of-the-emergency-court-of-appeals-1962/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-08-10T20:50:54-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2011-08-10:posts/2011/08/10/the-abolishment-of-the-emergency-court-of-appeals-1962/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the coming features at &lt;a href="http://courtlistener.com"&gt;CourtListener&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; for the law. Part of that feature is going to be some basic information about the courts themselves, so I spent some time over the weekend researching courts that served a special purpose but were since&amp;nbsp;abolished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such court was the &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Emergency_Court_of_Appeals"&gt;Emergency Court of Appeals&lt;/a&gt;. It was created during World War &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt; to set prices, and, naturally, was the court of appeals for many cases. The creation date of the court is prominently published in various places on the Internet, but the abolishment history of the court was very difficult to find. After researching online for some time, and learning that my library card had expired (sigh), I put in a query with the &lt;a href="http://www.loc.gov"&gt;Library of Congress&lt;/a&gt;, which provides free research of these types of&amp;nbsp;things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a couple days, the provided me with this amazing response, 
 which I&amp;#8217;m sharing here, and on the above Wikipedia&amp;nbsp;article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated in the Legislative Notes to 50 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; Code Appendix § 921 to 926, 
as posted at http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode50a/usc_sec_50a_00000921&amp;#8212;&amp;#8212;000-notes.html, 
the following explanation is given regarding the amendment and repeal of Act 
of Jan. 30, 1942, ch. 26, title &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt;, § 204, 56 Stat. 23,&amp;nbsp;31-33: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Section 924, acts Jan. 30, 1942, ch. 26, title &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt;, § 204, 
56 Stat. 31; June 30, 1944, ch. 325, title I, § 107, 58 Stat. 639; June 30, 
1945, ch. 214, § 6, 59 Stat. 308; July 30, 1947, ch. 361, title I, § 101, 
61 Stat. 619; June 25, 1948, ch. 646, § 32(a), 62 Stat. 991; May 24, 1949, 
ch. 139, § 127, 63 Stat. 107, authorized review of orders of the Office of 
Price Administrator under the Emergency Price Control Act of 1942, 
and created the Emergency Court of Appeals for this purpose. The Emergency 
Price Control Act of 1942 terminated on June 30, 1947, 
under the provisions of act July 25, 1946, ch. 671, § 1, 
60 Stat. 664. The Housing and Rent Act of 1948, act Mar. 30, 1948, ch. 161, 
62 Stat. 93, classified to section 1881 of this Appendix, 
continued the Court for the purpose of reviewing recommendations of local 
advisory boards for the decontrol or adjustment of maximum rents. Later, 
the Defense Production Act of 1950, act Sept. 8, 1950, ch. 932, 
64 Stat. 798, classified to sections 2061 to 2166 of this Appendix, 
continued the Court to review regulations and orders relating to price 
control. The Housing and Rent Act of 1948 and the Defense Production Act of 
1950 both terminated, however, the Court remained in existence &amp;#8220;to complete 
the adjudication of rights and liabilities incurred prior to their 
termination dates.&amp;#8221; (Transcript of Proceedings of the Final Session of the 
Court, 299 F.2d 1.) The final decision of the Court, Rosenzweig v. General 
Services Administration, 1961, 299 F.2d 22, was decided on Dec. 6, 
1961. A petition for rehearing was denied on Jan. 2, 1962, 
and a petition for writ of certiorari to the Supreme Court of the United 
States was denied on Mar. 19, 1962, 82 S. Ct.&amp;nbsp;830. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The order of Chief Judge Albert B. Maris, set forth in 299 F.2d 20,&amp;nbsp;provided: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business of this Court having been completed, it is ordered that at the
expiration of 30 days from this date, if a petition for certiorari has not 
been filed in the Supreme Court in Case No. 676 [Rosenzweig v. General 
Services Administration], just decided, the acting clerk shall deliver the 
records and papers of the Court in his office to the General Services 
Administration for permanent custody as records of the Government, 
and shall thereupon inform the Chief Justice of the United States that the 
work of the Court has been completed and that the designations of the judges
 of the Court may therefore appropriately be&amp;nbsp;terminated. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a petition for certiorari is filed in Case No. 676 this order shall take
effect and be carried out at the expiration of 30 days after the final 
disposition of Case No.&amp;nbsp;676.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In accordance with the terms of this order, the petition for certiorari 
having been filed, and denied Mar. 19, 1962, the Court terminated on Apr. 18,&amp;nbsp;1962.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty fantastic research. And for free! Thanks &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOC&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="loc"></category><category term="law"></category><category term="history"></category><category term="CourtListener"></category><category term="api"></category></entry><entry><title>Project Idea: “Community-Curated Data Repository”</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2010/08/02/project-idea-community-curated-data-repository/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-08-02T13:02:42-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2010-08-02:posts/2010/08/02/project-idea-community-curated-data-repository/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s an interesting problem that I&amp;#8217;ve run into a number of times that goes 
like this: You want to start a new project studying &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; dump of 
data, and you have a great idea of how to do &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; with it. You 
go download the data, but then you spend hours (days and weeks) manipulating 
it, manicuring it, and stuffing it neatly into a database. The problem is that 
the data is in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; format, and they probably haven&amp;#8217;t told you much 
about it, much less put it into a useful format for other people. You have no 
option but to figure it out, optimize it, make it queryable, etc, when really, 
what you wish you were doing was simply &lt;em&gt;working with it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the data format and quality keeps you from working with the 
data itself. I&amp;#8217;ve run into this a number of times, most notably when trying to 
work with the &lt;a href="http://www.recovery.gov/FAQ/Pages/DownLoadCenter.aspx"&gt;Recovery 
Data&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#8217;ve also had fun working with &lt;a href="http://census.gov"&gt;census 
data&lt;/a&gt;, geographic data, and the list goes on. There are any number of useful 
data sources that are provided by non-profits and government bodies, such as 
population, economic, health, and agricultural&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this problem is simple. A community needs to be built around 
curating the data and providing it in useful formats, and a repository of some 
sort needs to be made so people can download &lt;em&gt;and install&lt;/em&gt; the data. 
Similar ideas have come up a few times in various formats. Most notably, 
Google has taken a stab at solving this with their &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/publicdata/home" 
target="_blank"&gt;public data sets&lt;/a&gt;, and back around the turn of the 
millennium, Debian &lt;a href="http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=38902" 
target="_blank"&gt;considered making a repository&lt;/a&gt; for the&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of these solutions are good enough though. In Google&amp;#8217;s case, they&amp;#8217;re 
providing a one-way street: They choose the data source, they tune-up the 
data, and they provide the data. If there&amp;#8217;s a source you don&amp;#8217;t like, or if 
it&amp;#8217;s in a format you don&amp;#8217;t like, well, too bad. In the case of Debian, they 
decided not to go for it, but they should have. They had the right idea, but 
weren&amp;#8217;t prepared to give the idea its&amp;nbsp;due.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right solution will be one in which the community can suggest and debate 
data sources, and which treats the data with the respect it deserves. I think 
we&amp;#8217;ll see a data source like this eventually, but I fear that until we do, 
researchers around the world will be stuck doing unnecessary data&amp;nbsp;transformations.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="recovery"></category><category term="Project idea"></category><category term="debian"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="curation"></category></entry><entry><title>The eBook Wars Continue, but The Gravy Train Hasn’t Arrived</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2010/07/24/the-ebook-wars-continue-but-the-gravy-train-has-not-arrived/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-07-24T17:15:23-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2010-07-24:posts/2010/07/24/the-ebook-wars-continue-but-the-gravy-train-has-not-arrived/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Friends, I hate to be a wet towel, but do us all a favor: Don&amp;#8217;t buy an ebook reader yet. I know, I know, Amazon just dropped the price of the Kindle by like 30% or something, which is very cool, but better things are coming if we vote with our&amp;nbsp;feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current eBook readers that are on the market are gaining steam rapidly, and, yes, the devices are actually pretty cool, but there are some real problems with what we&amp;#8217;re being offered. Today, I read that &lt;a href="http://www.crunchgear.com/2010/07/22/amazon-strikes-sweet-exclusive-deal-good-for-them-bad-for-consumers/"&gt;Amazon just signed an exclusivity deal with a publisher,&lt;/a&gt; guaranteeing that the books by that publisher will only be distributed in paper and to the Kindle. This means that if you have any other eBook reader, you will have to buy the book in print, and won&amp;#8217;t be able to download&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably don&amp;#8217;t think this is a big deal, just as you didn&amp;#8217;t think buying CDs was a big deal ten years ago, but if you&amp;#8217;re like me, these days you consider buying CDs to be old school, and would rather sit at home and buy the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MP3&lt;/span&gt; over the Internet. Downloading MP3s has become easier than buying CDs, and similarly, in another couple years, buying eBooks will be most people&amp;#8217;s preferred method of getting a book &amp;mdash; that is, if we have certain freedoms when buying electronic&amp;nbsp;books. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal Amazon just signed is going to prompt the competition to try to make similar deals with other publishers, with the result being a fractured market for eBooks. If you want this book, you have to have a Kindle. If you want that book, you have to have a Nook. Etc. Right now, that isn&amp;#8217;t too annoying since eBooks aren&amp;#8217;t yet that popular, but once eBooks become the norm, this is going to get more and more frustrating for all of&amp;nbsp;us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of this problem, there are other issues with the current eBook ecosystem. For me to switch to using and buying eBooks, I want to be able to do the same things that I can do with real books. I want to be able to share them with my friends. I want them to be in a format that I can keep for decades, read again at a later date, and give to my children. I want to be able to bookmark and underline things, and use them on multiple&amp;nbsp;devices. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some movements towards these directions, but until Amazon stops with the exclusivity deals, and all the other eBook readers stop with their locked down devices, it looks like I&amp;#8217;ll be voting with my wallet, and staying out of the&amp;nbsp;game. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="nook"></category><category term="kindle"></category><category term="ebook"></category><category term="content"></category></entry><entry><title>Project Idea: “Bug Trackers for Cities.”</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2010/06/22/project-idea-bug-tracker-for-cities/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-06-22T16:59:02-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2010-06-22:posts/2010/06/22/project-idea-bug-tracker-for-cities/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, today&amp;#8217;s project idea was to post about the use of bug trackers for the management of city problems, but as it should turn out, I&amp;#8217;m behind the curve on this one, so I&amp;#8217;ll just explain the concept, and post some links to people that have live implementations or have already blogged about this. When I first researched this idea about six months ago, I didn&amp;#8217;t find anything, but it seems that steam is building behind this&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the idea is this: Cities have problems that citizens know about such as potholes, busted lampposts, gang activity, etc. They want to report these things to the city, but unfortunately reporting the problems by the phone or navigating the city websites is usually an awful, time-consuming, and unrewarding experience. It goes like this: First you get bumped from one department to another, eventually finding somebody who seems like they care. You tell them about the problem and feel satisfied that you&amp;#8217;ve done your part, but you don&amp;#8217;t know if it&amp;#8217;s really in their system, or when it&amp;#8217;s going to get fixed or anything. You hang up the phone, and the problem is still a part of your daily life. You know if you call again, you won&amp;#8217;t be able to get an update, and you resign yourself to simply &lt;em&gt;hoping&lt;/em&gt; that the problem will eventually be resolved. The next time you notice something that&amp;#8217;s in need of fixing, you&amp;#8217;re less likely to try to help. As this goes on, eventually the people that once cared no longer do, and getting residents of a city engaged in the problems in their community becomes increasingly&amp;nbsp;difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the software world, there is a similar phenomenon, except instead of infrastructure and safety problems, the problems are errors in the software that need to be fixed &amp;ndash; bugs. The solution to getting these bugs triaged and managed is to use what&amp;#8217;s known as a &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Bug_tracking_system"&gt;bug tracker&lt;/a&gt;. These systems allow the programmers behind the software to respond to problems that people find, and to triage them appropriately. In addition, they allow other people to vote on bugs, and help solve them. They allow careful prioritization of the bugs, and they allow visualizations of the bugs to be created such as the speed that they are fixed by department, the oldest bug in the system,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If such as system were used for citizens to track problems they find in their city, it would have all kinds of benefits, and indeed a few such systems have been created. The most popular that I have found is called &lt;a href="http://seeclickfix.com/"&gt;SeeClickFix&lt;/a&gt;, and looking at &lt;a href="http://seeclickfix.com/berkeley"&gt;the page for Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;, it seems like it is a system that is at least used by Berkeley residents. Another popular one is &lt;a href="http://www.fixmystreet.com/"&gt;http://www.fixmystreet.com/&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, for the system to be truly effective, it would have to be endorsed by the city itself, and used by its employees as well, which is something I have yet to find an example&amp;nbsp;of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other people have also &lt;a href="http://speedbird.wordpress.com/2010/04/22/frameworks-for-citizen-responsiveness/"&gt;written about this idea&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://portlandwiki.org/CivicApps#Notes_from_CivicApps_Meetup_at_Open_Source_Bridge_2010"&gt;Portland appears to be considering it&lt;/a&gt;, so it seems this idea is ripe on the vine and ready to be&amp;nbsp;picked. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question now is what will it take to implement it correctly, and what system will be the one that gains usage. I fully expect to see more cities using this type of technology in the next few&amp;nbsp;years. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="urban development"></category><category term="policy"></category><category term="bugs"></category><category term="Project idea"></category></entry><entry><title>Berkman Broadband Study</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2010/03/15/berkman-broadband-study/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-03-15T22:18:06-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2010-03-15:posts/2010/03/15/berkman-broadband-study/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month the Berkman Center at Harvard, under the guidance of Yokai Benkler, published a &lt;a href="http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/pubrelease/broadband/"&gt;200+ page document&lt;/a&gt; describing the broadband situation in the United States. The document is an absolute must read if you use the Internet (and you do if you&amp;#8217;re reading this), but before I share some real analysis of it (another time and post), I just wanted to share this quote discussing the best network bundle available in the world today:&lt;blockquote&gt;[The best] currently available [bundle] includes 100Mbps service to the home, digital &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HD&lt;/span&gt; and the ability to create your own private television channel for others to watch on their &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; sets, unlimited voice telephony throughout France and to 70 other countries, including the U.S., and secure nomadic Wi-Fi access wherever one&amp;#8217;s laptop or Wi-Fi-enabled phone is within range of the Freebox of any other Free subscriber in the country (24% of the French market), for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USD32&lt;/span&gt;.59 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; a month.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the $40 I spend per month for a tenth that Internet speed and nothing else, my mind is&amp;nbsp;blown.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="network"></category><category term="open access"></category><category term="fcc"></category><category term="France"></category></entry><entry><title>Some Legal Gems</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/12/12/some-legal-gems/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-12-12T23:11:37-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-12-12:posts/2009/12/12/some-legal-gems/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As anybody who has been following my &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/mlissner"&gt;twitter stream&lt;/a&gt; today knows, I have been spending the entire day hunting, pecking, avoiding, and kind of working on my final exam for my &lt;a href="http://people.ischool.berkeley.edu/~bcarver/mediawiki/index.php/Intellectual_Property_Law_for_the_Information_Industries_Syllabus"&gt;Intellectual Property Law Class&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While working on the exam, I have found some real legal gems today. These 
kinds of things don&amp;#8217;t often turn up unless you know to look for them, and 
since I&amp;#8217;m betting nobody ever looks, I figured I&amp;#8217;d share them&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, a warm up. May I present the laws that protects the &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode18/usc_sec_18_00000706----000-.html"&gt;Red Cross&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00220506----000-.html"&gt;The Olympics&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Or, perhaps the ones that define and protect (sort of) America&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00000301----000-.html"&gt;anthem (Star Spangled Banner)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00000302----000-.html"&gt;motto (&amp;#8220;In God we trust&amp;#8221;)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00000303----000-.html"&gt;floral emblem (the rose)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00000304----000-.html"&gt;march (Stars and Stripes Forever)&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00000305----000-.html"&gt;tree (the mighty oak)&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe you&amp;#8217;d prefer a &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sup_01_36_06_I_08_A_10_1.html"&gt;list of the national observances&lt;/a&gt; that are codified by law, such as the May, the &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00000139----000-.html"&gt;Steelmark month&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And finally, those laws that &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sup_01_36_06_I_08_A_10_5.html"&gt;govern the inauguration&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode36/usc_sec_36_00000504----000-.html"&gt;the regulations of the electricity&lt;/a&gt; that&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America, sometimes you have the strangest&amp;nbsp;laws.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="law"></category><category term="patriotism"></category><category term="red cross"></category><category term="olympics"></category></entry><entry><title>Technology Revolution and the Fourth Amendment</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/12/08/technology-revolution-and-the-fourth-amendment/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-12-08T12:29:15-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-12-08:posts/2009/12/08/technology-revolution-and-the-fourth-amendment/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I realized today that for some reason I never posted &lt;a href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/pdfs/tech-revolution-4th-amendment.pdf"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; back in May
when I wrote it. This paper is a brief analysis of the ways that our 
fourth amendment rights are being daily eroded by technology marching on. 
I didn&amp;#8217;t go too deeply into the importance of the fourth amendment (I 
probably should have), but if you&amp;#8217;re not up on your rights (or lack 
thereof), you might find this to be interesting&amp;nbsp;reading.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Technology Revolution"></category><category term="Fourth Amendment"></category><category term="Constitution"></category></entry><entry><title>Jacobsen v. Katzer Article Posted</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/10/03/jacobsen-v-katzer-article-posted/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-10-03T21:52:21-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-10-03:posts/2009/10/03/jacobsen-v-katzer-article-posted/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I finally finished an article I have been writing for Wikipedia, as part of my &lt;a href="http://people.ischool.berkeley.edu/~bcarver/mediawiki/index.php/INFO_237_Fall_2009_Syllabus"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt; Law class&lt;/a&gt;. The professor for this class is the same as the one that taught the Cyberlaw class I took in the Spring, and once again, he has asked us to work on Wikipedia as part of our&amp;nbsp;classwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were able to choose an article on Wikipedia that was related to the class, and I chose to work on the article on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacobsen_v._Katzer"&gt;Jacobsen v. Katzer&lt;/a&gt;, which is a very important case as it relates to open source licensing, patent law, copyright, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DMCA&lt;/span&gt;, and just about every other possible &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt; law&amp;nbsp;issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it was a very complicated case because Katzer has attempted to throw the book at Jacobsen (and vice versa). The court has not yet resolved all the issues, but from reading through about half of the court documents that &lt;a href="http://jmri.sourceforge.net/k/docket/index.shtml"&gt;Jacobsen has posted&lt;/a&gt;, it appears that Katzer&amp;nbsp;has:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patented technology that was not his to&amp;nbsp;patent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempted to get licensing fees from Jacobsen for those&amp;nbsp;patents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stolen the intellectual property of an open source project, stripped it of its license and then incorporated it into his own commercial&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempted to sue Jacobsen for copyright violation for something - I&amp;#8217;m not even sure&amp;nbsp;what&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And more - see the article for&amp;nbsp;details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, it&amp;#8217;s a nasty, nasty case, but ultimately it should work out for Jacobsen, and he should come out the better (or at least none the worse). At a minimum, he has to prove that the patents are invalid, Katzer stole his &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt;, and that he didn&amp;#8217;t steal Katzer&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt; - a walk in the&amp;nbsp;park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, that&amp;#8217;s easier said than done, but he&amp;#8217;s fighting what appears to be the good fight, and it looks like if he keeps at it, he will win in the&amp;nbsp;end.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="patent"></category><category term="paper"></category><category term="open source"></category><category term="Jacobsen v. Katzer"></category><category term="FOIA"></category><category term="DMCA"></category><category term="copyright"></category></entry><entry><title>Impossibility of Complete Privacy</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/07/14/impossibility-of-complete-privacy/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-07-14T10:56:35-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-07-14:posts/2009/07/14/impossibility-of-complete-privacy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short quote for you today from &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=721642"&gt;Property, Privacy and Personal Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by Paul M. Schwartz:&lt;blockquote&gt;Already in the offline world, and in no small irony, direct marketers generate and sell lists of people who have expressed an interest in protecting their privacy.&lt;/blockquote&gt;In other words, even if you don&amp;#8217;t participate, you&amp;#8217;ve participated.&amp;nbsp;Gotcha.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="privacy"></category><category term="metadata"></category></entry><entry><title>The Difficulties of Managing Online Estates</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/05/15/one-more-project-posted-the-difficulties-of-managing-online-estates/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-05-15T12:22:02-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-05-15:posts/2009/05/15/one-more-project-posted-the-difficulties-of-managing-online-estates/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, one more paper down, one more to go! Today I completed the final paper 
for &lt;a href="http://courses.ischool.berkeley.edu/i205/s09/index.html"&gt;my class on information law and policy&lt;/a&gt;, which was one of my best 
classes this semester. It was a pretty tough one that required a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of 
reading and a lot of extra work for the assignments, but I found it quite 
rewarding in the&amp;nbsp;end. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="{filenames}/pdfs/online-estates.pdf"&gt;attached assignment&lt;/a&gt; is in a similar vein to the one I posted on 
Tuesday, but approaches the topic from a slightly different angle. The assignment in 
this case was to present an analysis of some of the policy problems that are 
raised by a project of our choice. Since I had already done a lot of thinking 
about the policy implications of how we handle online assets after a death, I 
decided to analyze some of the problems that are raised, and to postulate some 
solutions of my&amp;nbsp;own.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="thanatosensitivity"></category><category term="paper"></category></entry><entry><title>Final Paper on Online Memorialization by Default</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/05/13/final-paper-on-online-memorialization-by-default/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-05-13T11:25:10-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-05-13:posts/2009/05/13/final-paper-on-online-memorialization-by-default/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I had an epic writing session, and finished &lt;a href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/pdfs/online-grieving.pdf"&gt;my final paper&lt;/a&gt; for
my class on the social and organizational issues of&amp;nbsp;information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topic of my paper was a bit on the morbid side, but somehow that&amp;#8217;s what
 I&amp;#8217;m doing a lot of work on this semester. The concept for the paper is 
 that as more and more people create and have online profiles on social 
 networking sites, a system is created where more and more people have an 
 online memorial when they die, whether they intend to or&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic became interesting to me about a year ago when my friend Blake 
Bigler died of a sudden heart attack (at the age of 25). Immediately 
afterwards, his Facebook page became a memorial to him where friends posted
 messages, pictures and the like. To this day, friends still wish him a 
 happy birthday, and post notes on his&amp;nbsp;page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that this was a dramatic change to the way that deaths occur and 
are memorialized, and that it needed to be analyzed more carefully, 
and so my paper was born. If you&amp;#8217;re interested, please feel free to&amp;nbsp;read.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="paper"></category><category term="thanatosensitivity"></category><category term="memorialization"></category></entry><entry><title>Quiet Friday News About CIA Interrogation Techniques</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/04/17/quiet-friday-afternoon-news-about-cia-interrogation-techniques/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-04-17T18:36:34-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-04-17:posts/2009/04/17/quiet-friday-afternoon-news-about-cia-interrogation-techniques/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;#8217;s a quiet Friday afternoon here in America, so that can mean only one thing: it&amp;#8217;s time for organizations to release whatever news they&amp;#8217;ve been trying to keep quiet for the week. This weeks&amp;#8217; big news is that a number of memos authorizing, rationalizing and generally condoning torture and interrogation &lt;a href="http://news.google.com/news?pz=1&amp;ncl=1334762857&amp;topic=h"&gt;have been released to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACLU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a couple of interesting facts here.  The first is that &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; few of the 3,000 or so news articles about this topic seem to link to the &lt;a href="http://www.aclu.org/safefree/general/olc_memos.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACLU&lt;/span&gt; site where the memos are prominently featured&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; I find this odd, and it gives me plenty of room for speculation. (Bad reporting? Laziness? Suppression? Something&amp;nbsp;else?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second interesting thing is the quotes in the memos themselves. I haven&amp;#8217;t had a chance to read all the memos yet, but I didn&amp;#8217;t have any difficulty finding some good stuff. The memos begin with a classic &amp;#8220;Top Secret&amp;#8221; stamp, and go on to say things such as:&lt;blockquote&gt;&amp;#8230;You would like to employ ten techniques&amp;#8230;These ten techniques are: (1) attention grasp, (2) Walling, (3) facial hold, (4) facial slap (insult slap), (5) cramped confinement, (6) wall standing, (7) stress positions, (8) sleep deprivation, (9) insects placed in a confinement box, and (10) the waterboard&lt;/blockquote&gt;
From a different memo:&lt;blockquote&gt;Detainees subject to sleep deprivation who are also subject to nudity as a separate interrogation technique will at times be nude and wearing a diaper. If the detainee is wearing a diaper, it is checked regularly and changed as necessary&amp;#8230;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They go on from there with great detail about how the interrogations go down, with the conclusion of course being that these things don&amp;#8217;t constitute&amp;nbsp;torture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; The math was done crudely. &lt;a href="http://news.google.com/news?pz=1&amp;ncl=1334762857&amp;topic=h"&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; a google search that turns up 2,890 hits on the topic, and &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;num=20&amp;q=link%3Ahttp%3A%2F%2Fwww.aclu.org%2Fsafefree%2Fgeneral%2Folc_memos.html+interrogation+memo&amp;btnG=Search"&gt;here&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; one that searches for sites that link to aclu.org, and that have the words &amp;#8220;interrogation memo&amp;#8221;. The method is crude, but the overlap is&amp;nbsp;sparse.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="news"></category><category term="torture"></category><category term="cia"></category><category term="interrogation"></category><category term="ACLU"></category></entry><entry><title>Who Is Entitled to Grieve and Why</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/04/13/who-is-entitled-to-grieve-and-why/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-04-13T19:39:27-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-04-13:posts/2009/04/13/who-is-entitled-to-grieve-and-why/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been doing some research about how the Internet changes the way we 
handle and cope with real life death, and I found a good quote today. It&amp;#8217;s 
not exactly about the Internet and death, but it&amp;#8217;s interesting to think 
about ways the Interne  may have made relationships more complex and how 
that has affected who is socially allowed to&amp;nbsp;grieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=memorializing%20loved%20ones%20on%20the%20world%20wide%20web"&gt;Memorializing Loved Ones on the World Wide 
Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are unwritten but familiar rules, however, about who is entitled to
grieve. Pine, for example, claimed that in &amp;#8220;compartmentalized society, 
funerals tend to be limited primarily to the &amp;#8216;proper&amp;#8217; bereaved people. This
has helped to create an underclass of grievers whose legitimacy may not 
even be recognized and whose needs are not addressed.&amp;#8221; Doka (1989) 
identified these individuals as disenfranchised grievers: those whose grief
occurs in relationships with no recognizable kin ties; those whose loss is 
not socially defined as significant; and those who are perceived to be 
incapable of grief (e.g., young children, very old adults, 
mentally-disabled persons)&amp;#8230;As relationships become more complex, 
the likelihood of disenfranchised grief and disenfranchised death&amp;nbsp;increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As somebody who has lost a couple of friends over the years that I was 
fairly close to (but not best friends with), this definitely hits&amp;nbsp;home.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="digital death"></category><category term="online grief"></category><category term="mourning"></category></entry><entry><title>An Analysis of FTC Behavioral Advertising and an End of Semester Countdown</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/04/02/analysis-of-ftc-behavioral-advertising/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-04-02T14:44:40-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-04-02:posts/2009/04/02/analysis-of-ftc-behavioral-advertising/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s coming down to the end of the semester, and after I finished &lt;a href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/pdfs/ftc.pdf"&gt;the 
attached paper&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FTC&lt;/span&gt; laws as the apply to online advertising, 
I did some calculations to figure out what I have to do&amp;nbsp;still. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out I have 68-95 pages to write (give or take), 
and two projects to complete between today and early May. Things are going 
to get&amp;nbsp;interesting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lay of the land looks like&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two law/policy papers - total of 35-50&amp;nbsp;pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One sociology paper - 25-35&amp;nbsp;pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A final project combining some aesthetics work I have been&amp;nbsp;doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two technology strategy assessments - total of eight&amp;nbsp;pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And an online project - watch for this&amp;nbsp;soon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I&amp;#8217;ll reserve my thoughts on the attached analysis, but I tried to analyze the ways that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FTC&lt;/span&gt; regulates online advertising&amp;#8230;within an eight page&amp;nbsp;limit. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="principles"></category><category term="policy"></category><category term="paper"></category><category term="law"></category><category term="FTC"></category><category term="advertising"></category></entry><entry><title>Zeran v. AOL Paper Posted</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/03/18/zeran-v-aol-paper-posted/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-03-18T12:47:06-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-03-18:posts/2009/03/18/zeran-v-aol-paper-posted/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I normally would post my work here for posterity when I finished it, but my latest assignment was actually due online as a Wikipedia&amp;nbsp;article. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to flesh out the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeran_v._America_Online,_Inc."&gt;Zeran v. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; article, and man was it a lot of work. You take for granted the amount of labor that goes into a Wikipedia article until you write one&amp;nbsp;yourself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case itself is pretty interesting, if I do say so myself. It&amp;#8217;s one of the main cases that granted immunity to websites from the postings of third parties. What happened was that somebody posted some inflammatory T-shirts on an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOL&lt;/span&gt; bulletin board in 1995, and put down Kenneth Zeran&amp;#8217;s name and phone number. He got hundreds of phone calls threatening and berating him, and decided to sue &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOL&lt;/span&gt; as a result for distributing defamatory&amp;nbsp;materials. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for Zeran though, between the time that the materials were posted, and the time that he sued, Congress passed the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communications_Decency_Act"&gt;Communications Decency Act&lt;/a&gt;, which pretty much covers &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOL&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s back (and google&amp;#8217;s, and yahoo&amp;#8217;s, and youtube&amp;#8217;s, and pretty much everybody&amp;nbsp;else&amp;#8217;s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sucks to be Zeran, but in the words of &lt;a href="http://partners.nytimes.com/library/tech/00/02/cyber/cyberlaw/04law.html"&gt;one article on the subject&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;#8220;It&amp;#8230;illustrates a hard fact of life: Sometimes there is no legal remedy for those who suffer&amp;nbsp;wrongs.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, after all this, Zeran&amp;#8217;s phone number is still on whitepages.com. I wonder if he&amp;nbsp;knows&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="cyberlaw"></category><category term="paper"></category><category term="Zeran"></category><category term="AOL"></category></entry><entry><title>Confused About Obama</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/01/23/confused-about-obama/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-01-23T13:35:55-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-01-23:posts/2009/01/23/confused-about-obama/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You know, I was 18 when Bush came into power. I had embarrassingly weak knowledge of politics, and didn&amp;#8217;t vote in the election despite some people getting rather annoyed with me about it. I argued at the time (and I stand by this), that people should only vote if they know enough to vote the right way. At the time, I felt like I didn&amp;#8217;t know&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s hard to remember how things were back then. Bush was obviously an idiot, but at the same time, it wasn&amp;#8217;t obvious how much damage he would do (or that somehow he&amp;#8217;d last eight years). My first hint that he was terrible was his thinking on stem cells, which pretty indisputably slowed medicine research for about a decade. Once I heard about this issue, I knew I should have voted, and became fairly active reading the news and learning the&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, I can thank the Bush administration for being one of the most corrupt, damaging, and all-around God-awful regimes in American history. If it hadn&amp;#8217;t been so terrible, I might not have gotten so interested. I think this is true for many of my friends as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just spent some time looking at a few of &lt;a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing_room/executive_orders/"&gt;Obama&amp;#8217;s executive orders and memos&lt;/a&gt;, and of the few I read, it&amp;#8217;s pretty impressive. It&amp;#8217;s been less than a week, and suddenly I&amp;#8217;m having a lot more trouble being critical of the administration. If I&amp;#8217;m not supposed to rag on Bush anymore, in a way, what do I do? Do I praise Obama? That&amp;#8217;s not really my style. Maybe I should be critical of the Obama administration? But there&amp;#8217;s not a lot to be too critical of just&amp;nbsp;yet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m a bit confused, in a good way. Here&amp;#8217;s to hoping that Obama can keep it up, and to a new&amp;nbsp;regime.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="politics"></category><category term="Obama"></category><category term="change"></category></entry><entry><title>The Interactions of Law and Code</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/01/22/the-interactions-of-law-and-code/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-01-22T10:35:59-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-01-22:posts/2009/01/22/the-interactions-of-law-and-code/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For my new Cyberlaw course, we were assigned a reading by Lawrence Lessig 
called &lt;a href="www.lessig.org/content/articles/works/finalhls.pdf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 
Law of the Horse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In it, he writes about how code can control law, and 
vise versa. He makes some good points that are intuitive yet bear saying 
nonetheless. Cyberspace as it currently exists is a largely unregulated domain. 
People can use it pretty much anonymously, so accountability is pretty limited. 
Lessig argues that this is because of the architecture of the Internet as it 
has been created by&amp;nbsp;programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Net grows, as its 
regulatory power increases, as its power as a source of values becomes 
established, the values of real-space sovereigns will at first lose out. In 
many cases, no doubt, that is a very good thing. But there is no reason to 
believe that it will be a good thing generally or indefinitely. There is 
nothing to guarantee that the regime of values constituted by code will be a 
liberal regime; and little reason to expect that an invisible hand of code 
writers will push it in that direction. Indeed, to the extent that code 
writers respond to the wishes of commerce, a power to control may well be the 
tilt that this code begins to take. Understanding this tilt will be a&lt;br /&gt;
continuing project of the law of&amp;nbsp;cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in other words, cyberspace is a good place these days, ruled by fairly 
liberal ideals, but there is no guarantee that it will stay that way, and we 
may eventually need more&amp;nbsp;regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="infotech"></category><category term="cyberlaw"></category><category term="Lessig"></category></entry><entry><title>Guantanamo to Close, But They’re Just Moving the Prisoners</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/01/12/guantanamo-to-close-but-they-are-just-moving-the-prisoners/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-01-12T23:17:53-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-01-12:posts/2009/01/12/guantanamo-to-close-but-they-are-just-moving-the-prisoners/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was happy to read the news today that &lt;a href="http://www.iht
.com/articles/2009/01/13/america/13gitmo.php?page=1"&gt;Obama 
plans to close Guantanamo Bay prison camp&lt;/a&gt;. This is good news for 
America, and should be good news for the prisoners&amp;nbsp;there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read up on it though, I was saddened to hear that the prisoners are 
just being moved to other countries. This is rather frustrating because as Noam Chomsky puts it &amp;mdash; and I&amp;#8217;m paraphrasing &amp;mdash; there&amp;#8217;s only one reason to have off-site &lt;del&gt;torture&lt;/del&gt; prison camps: to go around American&amp;nbsp;law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m really not sure what the point is in closing Guantanamo if it just means
 moving the prisoners elsewhere. Pretty stupid use of&amp;nbsp;resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a juicy quote from the&amp;nbsp;article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who have conferred with transition officials said the incoming 
administration appeared to have rejected a proposal to seek a new law 
authorizing indefinite detention inside the United States. The Bush 
administration has insisted that such a measure is necessary to close the 
Guantanamo camp and bring some detainees to the United&amp;nbsp;States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, we could bring the prisoners to a camp in the U.S., 
but that would mean we couldn&amp;#8217;t hold them in tiny cells indefinitely, 
and that American law would be necessary. Wow. Can&amp;#8217;t have that, can&amp;nbsp;we?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="torture"></category><category term="prison camp"></category><category term="Obama"></category><category term="Cuba"></category></entry><entry><title>Research Idea – The Age of the Internet</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/01/05/research-idea-age-of-the-internet/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-01-05T15:41:47-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2009-01-05:posts/2009/01/05/research-idea-age-of-the-internet/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I blogged &lt;a href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/12/28/firefox-last-modified-tip/"&gt;a while back&lt;/a&gt; about a Firefox command that would tell you 
the last modified date of the page you were looking at, 
and it got me thinking&amp;#8230;.what is the age of the Internet on the&amp;nbsp;whole?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about it a bit, and it seems like knowing this kind of 
information could prove pretty useful for certain circles. If there was a 
way to summarize the last modified date of every page on the Internet, 
we could pretty easily figure out how useful the information&amp;nbsp;is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox&amp;nbsp;add-on? &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Internet"></category><category term="Project idea"></category></entry><entry><title>Dear Mr. Gore</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/12/29/dear-mr-gore/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-12-29T22:55:21-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-12-29:posts/2008/12/29/dear-mr-gore/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Honorable Al Gore
2100 West End Avenue, Suite 260
Nashville, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TN&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;37203&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;29 December&amp;nbsp;2008&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr.&amp;nbsp;Gore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I applaud your efforts towards educating the world on the subject of 
anthropogenic climate change, and I congratulate you on your Nobel&amp;nbsp;Prize. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write today to urge you to adopt a more open copyright on your materials. 
From what I can deduce, you are relying on the standard American copyright 
for your movie, presentations and books. As a lawyer, 
I am sure you are aware that this copyright system gives you incredible 
strength to protect the fruit of your efforts, however for many people, 
this system hampers their access to reading your books, 
watching your movie, or enjoying your&amp;nbsp;presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IPCC&lt;/span&gt; have been recognized as the greatest laborers towards 
educating the world on this subject, and I understand if you have taken the 
traditional route with your work. Recently however, as I began purchasing 
the third copy of your movie to give away to a friend, 
I couldn&amp;#8217;t help but think about how great it would be if it were simply 
streamed from your&amp;nbsp;site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many options for creating a more open copyright system, 
and I hope you will take the time to consider the implications of your 
current&amp;nbsp;method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael&amp;nbsp;Lissner&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="copyright"></category><category term="climate change"></category><category term="global warming"></category></entry><entry><title>Cheney is so shady, it pisses me off.</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/12/19/cheney-is-so-fing-shady-it-pisses-me-off/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-12-19T21:35:28-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-12-19:posts/2008/12/19/cheney-is-so-fing-shady-it-pisses-me-off/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Cheney is &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5jz2z92QFdgFrIMAJC-4GQcHOm3MgD955ETCO0"&gt;at work&lt;/a&gt; to keep his records from becoming public as part of 
the National Archives when he goes out of&amp;nbsp;office. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vice president alone may determine what constitutes vice presidential
 records or personal records, how his records will be created, maintained, 
 managed and disposed, and are all actions that are committed to his 
 discretion by&amp;nbsp;law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can think of no reason why this would be necessary unless he&amp;#8217;s the shadiest 
person ever in office. Oh,&amp;nbsp;right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an ex-government worker, I can testify to how ridiculous this is: It&amp;#8217;s 
really fucking&amp;nbsp;ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="rant"></category><category term="archive"></category><category term="cheney"></category><category term="government"></category></entry><entry><title>To Be Silent is To Lie</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/12/05/to-be-silent-is-to-lie/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-12-05T17:01:32-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-12-05:posts/2008/12/05/to-be-silent-is-to-lie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="http://michaeljaylissner.com/images/eagle-badge.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C. William Steele&lt;br /&gt;
Director&lt;br /&gt;
National Eagle Scout Association&lt;br /&gt;
1325 West Walnut Hill Lane&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;P.O.&lt;/span&gt; Box 152079&lt;br /&gt;
Irving, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TX&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;75015-2079  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 December&amp;nbsp;2008&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes to be Silent is to&amp;nbsp;Lie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;Miguel de&amp;nbsp;Unamuno&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr.&amp;nbsp;Steele:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was four years old, I was a Tiger Scout. Later, I became a Cub Scout,
 and then a Webelos. When I was old enough, I became a Boy Scout. Over the 
 next few years, I advanced in rank, became an Eagle Scout and achieved many
  Eagle Palms. I had over 100 merit badges, was the Junior Assistant 
  Scoutmaster, went on the National Jamboree in Arlington, Virginia, 
  and the International Jamboree in&amp;nbsp;Chile. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was what could be considered one hell of a Boy Scout. Today, 
with much bitterness and sadness, I give up the only remaining symbol of 
those parts of my life. Today, I return to you my Eagle Scout Badge, 
and in so doing, renounce and reject the prejudices and discriminative 
practices of the Boy Scouts of&amp;nbsp;America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was about 16, I learned that agnostics, atheists and gays would not 
be tolerated by the policies of the Boy Scouts. While it&amp;#8217;s true that as of 
2000, the supreme court backs your (well-funded) position as a private 
organization to discriminate institutionally, that does not make it right. 
Each of these positions flies in the face of scouting elsewhere in the 
world, and each of them reinforces an environment in which people with 
different opinions are awarded different value. While it is true that Baden 
Powell said that &amp;#8220;[no] man is much good unless he believes in God and obeys 
His laws,&amp;#8221; we sometimes must reflect on the beliefs of our founders, 
and put them in the context of their day. When Baden Powell made this 
remark, women had not yet gained suffrage, Nazi Europe had yet to come and 
go, and apartheid had yet to be institutionalized, let alone dismantled. In 
short, it was a different&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must ask ourselves what are we doing today that our children will disdain.
Today we live in a world where religious differences can be enlightening 
and can lead to greater understanding of ourselves and our peers. Yet in 
this world, religion can be used publicly as an accusation (Obama as Muslim),
and defenses to such accusations need not defend the religion, 
only the man. We live in a world today where religious differences lead to 
war, terrorism, and deaths of thousands of people. We live in a world where 
an organization designed to create leaders out of boys discriminates based 
on religion and sexual preference. If we are not careful, 
our children and their children will not look kindly upon our time as one of
freedom of opinion and religion, but rather as one of oppression, war, 
and&amp;nbsp;discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your organization has at its heart some of the greatest lessons I have 
learned during my lifetime, and it saddens me greatly to be forced to 
abandon it. I plan to have children one day, and it saddens me greatly that
they will not have the Boy or Girl Scouts of America in their lives. Most 
of all though, it saddens me that a national organization would choose not 
to include a diversity of people and&amp;nbsp;opinions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enclosed is my Eagle Scout badge, one of my more treasured possessions. I 
hope some day to get it back from you, and I hope someday that you will 
realize the error of your&amp;nbsp;ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Lissner
Eagle Scout,&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8216;98&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="eagle scout"></category><category term="discrimination"></category><category term="boy scouts"></category></entry><entry><title>Rebuilding the 9th Ward in New Orleans</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/11/30/rebuilding-the-9th-ward-in-new-orleans/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-11-30T20:11:06-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-11-30:posts/2008/11/30/rebuilding-the-9th-ward-in-new-orleans/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve spent Thanksgiving in the Deep South this year at my girlfriend&amp;#8217;s 
grandparent&amp;#8217;s house. It&amp;#8217;s been a great trip, but one thing about it keeps 
plaguing&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent a couple of days in New Orleans, and one of the places I insisted upon 
seeing was the 9th Ward, where Katrina dealt some of the worst damage. I wanted 
to see if people were recovering, and how much the place had been fixed up 
since 2005 when the storm blew&amp;nbsp;through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What surprised me (aside from the &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bisset_linda/3026355210/"&gt;markings&lt;/a&gt;) is that people are moving 
back into this area, rebuilding their houses, and generally, pouring money into 
the location. On the one hand, it makes sense since it&amp;#8217;s their home, but on the 
other, I can&amp;#8217;t help but think that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;somebody&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; should stop 
this from happening. From what I&amp;#8217;ve learned while here, the 9th Ward is an area 
of New Orleans that is going to flood if there is another hurricane 
Katrina&amp;#8230;which there will be sooner or later. Considering that Katrina 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Katrina"&gt;killed almost 2,000 
people&lt;/a&gt; this seems rather&amp;nbsp;unwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, rather than moving back in, shouldn&amp;#8217;t we be cutting our losses right about 
now, finding somewhere for these people to live, and preventing another 
disaster? Or is my logic&amp;nbsp;flawed?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="policy"></category><category term="katrina"></category><category term="disaster"></category><category term="bad ideas"></category></entry><entry><title>A Music Cost Inventory</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/11/22/a-music-cost-inventory/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-11-22T17:21:02-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-11-22:posts/2008/11/22/a-music-cost-inventory/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://www.copyright.gov/title17/92chap5.html"&gt;Title 17, Chapter 5, section 504c2 of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; copyright law&lt;/a&gt;, if you get caught with music that you have downloaded illegally from the Internet, you can get charged up to $150,000 per infringement. I thought I would do a little experiment to see how much I would be in for if my entire collection were to be found to be&amp;nbsp;illegal. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s do some math. I have 3,876 tracks, at $150,000 each. So if my entire collection were to be found illegal, that means it would cost me $581.4 million dollars &amp;mdash; about .6 billion&amp;nbsp;dollars. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, let&amp;#8217;s assume that I can live with that reality. It just seems odd that I could have bought those songs for $3,876 on amazon.com, or&amp;nbsp;iTunes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something isn&amp;#8217;t quite right here. Also, did I mention that all &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; digital music sales &lt;a href="http://www.ifpi.org/content/section_resources/dmr2008.html"&gt;are estimated&lt;/a&gt; to total $2.9B in 2007? That makes my music worth about 20% of the 2007&amp;nbsp;revenue.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Music"></category><category term="Copyright"></category><category term="IP"></category><category term="Policy"></category><category term="Law"></category></entry><entry><title>Mr. Rogers on the Usage of VCRs</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/11/22/mr-rogers-on-the-usage-of-vcrs/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-11-22T17:13:23-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-11-22:posts/2008/11/22/mr-rogers-on-the-usage-of-vcrs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I found a good quote by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr_Rogers"&gt;Mr. Rogers&lt;/a&gt; himself today. I knew I always liked this guy. Too bad he couldn&amp;#8217;t live forever. This quote is a bit dated, but the point is still good. It also helps to imagine his voice before reading this:&lt;blockquote&gt;Some public stations, as well as commercial stations, program the &amp;#8220;Neighborhood&amp;#8221; at hours when some children cannot use it. I think that it&amp;#8217;s a real service to families to be able to record such programs and show them at appropriate times. I have always felt that with the advent of all this new technology that allows people to tape the &amp;#8220;Neighborhood&amp;#8221; off-the-air, and I&amp;#8217;m speaking for the &amp;#8220;Neighborhood&amp;#8221; because that&amp;#8217;s what I produce, that they then become much more active in the programming of their family&amp;#8217;s television life. Very frankly, I am opposed to people being programmed by others. My whole approach in broadcasting has always been &amp;#8220;You are an important person just the way you are. You can make healthy decisions.&amp;#8221; Maybe I&amp;#8217;m going on too long, but I just feel that anything that allows a person to be more active in the control of his or her life, in a healthy way, is important.&lt;/blockquote&gt;You tell them Mr. Rogers. You tell&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8216;em.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="copyright"></category><category term="VCR"></category><category term="IP"></category></entry><entry><title>Misdirected Energies</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/10/31/misguided-energies/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-10-31T00:07:18-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-10-31:posts/2008/10/31/misguided-energies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.rmi.org/images/PDFs/WTOE/WTOE.pdf"&gt;Winning the Oil Endgame&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (free login&amp;nbsp;required):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; light vehicle in 2003 had 24% more weight,
 93% more horsepower, and 29% faster 0-60-mph time than in 1981, 
 but only 1% more miles per gallon. If 1981 performance had instead stayed 
 constant, light vehicles would have become 33% more efficient&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s not a bad read, but it is 300+ pages of dense&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="oil"></category><category term="sustainability"></category></entry><entry><title>Excess Elections Spending</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/10/29/excess-elections-spending/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-10-29T14:16:35-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-10-29:posts/2008/10/29/excess-elections-spending/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re just about to the line here with the election, and I, for one, am really looking forward to a phone that stops ringing, to my mail carrier&amp;#8217;s back feeling better, and to my inbox devoid of political&amp;nbsp;emails. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, things have gotten out of control. In an &lt;a href="http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5iXAkBilVhjbpsgAAHfgp6kGEShvwD944BQP84"&gt;article by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AP&lt;/span&gt; today&lt;/a&gt;, the Republicans said that they were going to: &lt;blockquote&gt;&amp;#8220;&amp;#8230;send out over 200 million pieces of mail and have over a quarter of a billion contacts, counting the mail, the phones and the door knocks,&amp;#8221;&lt;/blockquote&gt;According to the 2000 census, there are about 227 million people in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; over the age 18. What that means is that if &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ONLY&lt;/span&gt; the republican party &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ONLY&lt;/span&gt; contacted me regarding the presidential race, they would still do so more than one&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, both parties contact me at all levels of government from city to county to state to federal. And they both do it for each candidate, and every measure. Often they do it more than&amp;nbsp;once. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are there any numbers totalling the cost of elections nationwide? I&amp;#8217;d be interested in seeing such a thing. What else could we buy with that amount of&amp;nbsp;money? &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="elections"></category><category term="spam"></category></entry><entry><title>Piracy “Costs”</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/10/08/piracy-costs/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-10-08T14:12:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-10-08:posts/2008/10/08/piracy-costs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ars Technica has a &lt;a href="http://arstechnica.com/articles/culture/dodgy-digits-behind-the-war-on-piracy.ars/1"&gt;good article today&lt;/a&gt; about the costs of piracy where they debunk (in four glorious pages) two figures that are often cited to explain just how bad the piracy problem has&amp;nbsp;become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;#8217;ve done an excellent job showing that the figures are absolutely bogus, but their conclusion really makes quite a point. For reference, the first figure is that 750,000 jobs have been lost due to piracy, and the second is that piracy costs $200-$250&amp;nbsp;billion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a quote from the conclusion, after they have debunked both of the numbers:&lt;blockquote&gt;Neither figure is terribly plausible on its face. As Wired noted earlier this week, 750,000 jobs is fully 8 percent of the current number of unemployed in the United States. And $250 billion is more than the combined 2005 gross domestic revenues of the movie, music, software, and video game industries.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmmm&amp;#8230;sounds like these numbers might be a bit&amp;nbsp;exaggerated.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="piracy"></category><category term="bad statistics"></category></entry><entry><title>The Argument for Encryption, and Why Vista Is Irresponsible</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/09/26/the-argument-for-encryption-and-why-vista-is-irresponsible/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-09-26T20:34:31-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-09-26:posts/2008/09/26/the-argument-for-encryption-and-why-vista-is-irresponsible/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We all agree that security is necessary for our data, but we all fall down when it comes to implementation. An example that I keep returning to is the need for encryption. I posted a few days ago about how Yahoo! doesn&amp;#8217;t encrypt their email, allowing a sophisticated hacker to intercept any message to or from your&amp;nbsp;account. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I encountered my password in plain text in a configuration file that is easily accessible to anybody that gains physical access to my computer. The guilty program is the Pidgin &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; client (&lt;a href="http://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/5872"&gt;bug filed here&lt;/a&gt;), which stores login and password information in an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XML&lt;/span&gt; file in your home directory. I&amp;#8217;ve seen files of this sort a number of times, and for some reason programmers keep using this&amp;nbsp;technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people believe that if they have confidential information in their computers, and if they use a password on their computer, they&amp;#8217;ll be &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;. Nobody will be able to get past the password. While that isn&amp;#8217;t entirely true (most passwords are easily broken), the thing to remember is that once a hard drive is removed from a computer, any of the data on it can be accessed &amp;#8212; without the password. So, so long as programmers keep using this technique, sensitive data will still be out&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest solution to this problem is to encrypt your entire hard disk at all times. That way, even if your hard disk is removed from your computer, all the data is jumbled anyway. Ubuntu released this feature back in April, and Microsoft released this feature with the release of Vista. Unfortunately though, to receive encryption on your Vista installation, you have to buy Vista Ultimate, which costs $120 more than the Home version (&lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windows-vista/compare-editions/default.aspx"&gt;at a cool $320!&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we trust more and more data on our computers, is this irresponsible product engineering? Absolutely. It costs Microsoft no more money to put encryption on all versions. Unfortunately though, they make more money by charging for&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="microsoft"></category><category term="security"></category><category term="vista"></category><category term="pidgin"></category></entry><entry><title>On DRM and the Darknet</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/09/15/on-drm-and-the-darknet/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-09-15T21:09:43-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-09-15:posts/2008/09/15/on-drm-and-the-darknet/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just read &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;source=web&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=1&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fcrypto.stanford.edu%2FDRM2002%2Fdarknet5.doc&amp;ei=VTLPSLfdG5m0sQOo1ciIBw&amp;usg=AFQjCNHZkIYjxy6LnWvUSt6kGrZ3SYLMZQ&amp;sig2=hz865qMKNfakTgDi4sUVpA"&gt;an 
interesting paper&lt;/a&gt; written by some Microsoft engineers on the subject of 
the futures of darknets and illicit file sharing on the&amp;nbsp;Internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty interesting&amp;nbsp;stuff:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230;the darknet will be a competitor to legal commerce. From the point of 
view of economic theory, this has profound implications for business strategy: 
for example, increased security (e.g. stronger &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRM&lt;/span&gt; systems) may act as a
disincentive to legal commerce. Consider an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MP3&lt;/span&gt; file sold on a web site: this 
costs money, but the purchased object is as useful as a version acquired from 
the darknet. However, a securely &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRM&lt;/span&gt;-wrapped song is strictly less attractive: 
although the industry is striving for flexible licensing rules, customers will 
be restricted in their actions if the system is to provide meaningful&amp;nbsp;security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems so obvious, yet&amp;#8230;this paper was written several years&amp;nbsp;ago. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="microsoft"></category><category term="DRM"></category><category term="darknet"></category></entry><entry><title>Sarah Palin - Worst candidate of all time?</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/09/05/sarah-palin-worst-candidate-of-all-time/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-09-05T08:51:04-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-09-05:posts/2008/09/05/sarah-palin-worst-candidate-of-all-time/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been getting a lot of email lately from various organizations telling me about Sarah Palin. They&amp;#8217;ve started to pile up in my inbox, so I decided that I better learn a little about the woman. Here&amp;#8217;s what I learned so&amp;nbsp;far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She was mayor of a town so small it didn&amp;#8217;t have a police department&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She believes the Iraq war is &amp;#8220;a task from God.&amp;#8221;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Referring to a natural gas line she wanted built, she said, &amp;#8220;God&amp;#8217;s will has to be done in unifying people and companies to get that gas line built, so pray for that.&amp;#8221;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt; Gods will?&amp;nbsp;What? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She has been Governor of Alaska for about a year and a half. For the ten years or so prior to that, she was mayor of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TINY&lt;/span&gt; town of about 5,469 people.&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She opposes abortion in all cases except if the health of the mother is in danger. That includes rape and incest.&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As of 2006, she supported teaching creationism in schools. To wit: &amp;#8220;Teach both&amp;#8230;I am a proponent of teaching both.&amp;#8221;&lt;sup&gt;[5]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She sued the Bush administration for listing polar bears as a threatened species.&lt;sup&gt;[6]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we really want this person in any position of power? To reiterate, she was mayor of a town of about 5,000 people for the bulk of her time in politics, she believes she knows the will of God, she would have creationism in schools, she would have rape victims give birth to the rapist&amp;#8217;s child against their will, and is even more anti-environmental than the Bush&amp;nbsp;administration. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incredible. Please help get this word out. This is awful, and not just a passing&amp;nbsp;concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;1.&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.time.com/time/politics/article/0,8599,1837918,00.html"&gt;http://www.time.com/time/politics/article/0,8599,1837918,00.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;2.&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href="http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5jNulPSqaP1eyysv8ENJWhk0ZSrPgD92VJPL00"&gt;http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5jNulPSqaP1eyysv8ENJWhk0ZSrPgD92VJPL00&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;3.&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wasilla,_Alaska"&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wasilla,_Alaska&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;4.&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.juneauempire.com/stories/101906/sta_20061019031.shtml"&gt;http://www.juneauempire.com/stories/101906/sta_20061019031.shtml&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;5.&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href="http://dwb.adn.com/news/politics/elections/story/8347904p-8243554c.html"&gt;http://dwb.adn.com/news/politics/elections/story/8347904p-8243554c.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;6.&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/environment/article3987891.ece"&gt;http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/environment/article3987891.ece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="politics"></category><category term="palin"></category></entry><entry><title>Dear Hillary</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/05/20/dear-hillary/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-05-20T21:06:22-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-05-20:posts/2008/05/20/dear-hillary/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dear&amp;nbsp;Hillary, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems you have lost the contest, and it&amp;#8217;s time that you accept that fact. I won&amp;#8217;t say you ran a good race, but you really did put one heck of a lot of effort. By &lt;a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/21660914"&gt;my count&lt;/a&gt; though, there are 313 delegates remaining. Obama needs to get 72 of them. You need&amp;nbsp;243. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#8217;s time to throw in the towel, and - dare I say it - move on.&amp;nbsp;Please?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="politics"></category><category term="elections"></category></entry><entry><title>My Child Is NOT Catholic</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/03/09/my-child-is-not-catholic-dawkins-insists/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-03-09T10:34:27-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-03-09:posts/2008/03/09/my-child-is-not-catholic-dawkins-insists/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dawkins" src="http://michaeljaylissner.com/images/dawkins.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of going to see &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Dawkins"&gt;Richard Dawkins&lt;/a&gt; last night at Cal. 
Although our fourth-row seating probably influenced my judgement, 
I must say he is a truly excellent&amp;nbsp;speaker. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished his book, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_God_Delusion"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The God Delusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; several months ago, 
and I had to agree with a friend who said he was a bit &amp;#8220;heavy-handed&amp;#8221; in 
the book. So when I went to see him in person, I expected much the same. I 
expected him to push me, to drive his point, to be a little bit too 
aggressive in his delivery. To the contrary though, he is a subtle, 
interesting, humble, and actually quite a funny&amp;nbsp;speaker. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech, he engaged in &amp;#8220;consciousness raising&amp;#8221;, 
which he believes worked for feminism, and which he believes will work for 
religion. His example was that as a result of feminist consciousness 
raising, if I say: &amp;#8220;All men are created equal&amp;#8221;, you might think: &amp;#8220;Right, 
but what about the women?&amp;#8221; He wants to apply this tool to religion, 
so if I say: &amp;#8220;A Catholic child&amp;#8221;, you think: &amp;#8220;Children aren&amp;#8217;t Catholics - 
They&amp;#8217;re too young to know where they stand on such&amp;nbsp;issues.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He believes (and I must agree) that religion in the world has brought much 
violence and destruction, and that the whole thing could be cut off at the 
stem if we all realized that our children do not share our religion. I&amp;#8217;m 
simplifying and combining several of his points, but that was really the 
thrust of his speech. If I am a catholic, that does not make my child a 
catholic; I a Muslim, does not make my child a Muslim.&amp;nbsp;Etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To drive his point home, Dawkins showed a picture that he said he found on 
the Christmas cover of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/"&gt;Telegraph Newspaper&lt;/a&gt;. In the picture, 
were three children sitting side by side in costume for some Christmas event
(I think they were the three wise men or some such). The idea behind the 
picture was to depict religious harmony. To quote his&amp;nbsp;book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Christmas-time one year my daily newspaper, the Independent, 
was looking for a seasonal image and found a heart-warmingly ecumenical one
at a school nativity play. The Three Wise Men were played by, 
as the caption glowingly said, Shadbreet (a Sikh), 
Musharraf (a Muslim) and Adele (a Christian), all aged four. Charming? 
Heart-warming? No, it is not, it is neither; it is grotesque. [&amp;#8230;] Imagine 
an identical photograph, with the caption changed as follows: &amp;#8220;Shadbreet (a 
Keynesian), Musharaff (a Monetarist) and Adele (a Marxist), 
all aged four.&amp;#8221; Wouldn&amp;#8217;t this be a candidate for irate letters of protest? 
It certainly should&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;#8217;t say that I&amp;#8217;m one to really get &amp;#8220;irate&amp;#8221; about such things, 
but he really does have a point. The number of people that grow up to be the
same religion as their parents is astounding. How can it be that the 
religion of all peoples&amp;#8217; parents around the world just happens to be the 
right one for their children? It defies&amp;nbsp;logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Dawkins believes that if we raise consciousness in a similar way to 
feminism, and find a way to allow children to be nontheists until they are 
old enough to make such decisions on their own, we might just be able to 
beat thi  religion thing. We might be able to curb religious violence by 
allowing children to make their own&amp;nbsp;choices. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could work, and I for one am officially convinced that I will not let 
people speak of religious&amp;nbsp;children. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="me"></category><category term="atheism"></category><category term="Cal"></category></entry><entry><title>Federal Salaries</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/02/10/federal-salaries/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-02-10T12:02:17-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-02-10:posts/2008/02/10/federal-salaries/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just some food for thought from &lt;a href="http://thebudgetgraph.com"&gt;thebudgetgraph.com&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salary of William McGuire, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt; of UnitedHealth Group: &lt;strong&gt;$124M&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salary of Leslie Norwalk, Head Administrator of Medicare/Medicaid: &lt;strong&gt;$143,250&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salary of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt; of Walmart: &lt;strong&gt;$17.5M&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salary of Postmaster General of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USPS&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;$173,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highest paid federal employee, Army Football Coach Bobby Ross: &lt;strong&gt;$600,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;President&amp;#8217;s salary (perks aside): &lt;strong&gt;$400,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just to add some perspective, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USPS&lt;/span&gt; would be the 20th largest company above Meryl Lynch, if it were private (revenues of &lt;strong&gt;$78B&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medicare/Medicaid has a revenue of &lt;strong&gt;$565B&lt;/strong&gt;; UnitedHealth Group has &lt;strong&gt;$45.4B&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football is a&amp;nbsp;game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president rules the free world (more or&amp;nbsp;less). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Painful.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="taxes"></category><category term="political"></category></entry><entry><title>Top Five Problems with Major American Elections</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/01/20/top-five-problems-with-elections/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-01-20T13:04:07-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2008-01-20:posts/2008/01/20/top-five-problems-with-elections/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about elections a lot lately (even before that last post), and I&amp;#8217;ve come up with five things that are simply broken about democracy. Call me a commie or a socialist or something if you must, but I challenge you to identify why these are not critical flaws with our&amp;nbsp;system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number 1 - Money&lt;/strong&gt;
It&amp;#8217;s long been known that it&amp;#8217;s expensive to run for any political position, but how much does it really cost? Well, as of January 9, &lt;a href="http://blog.washingtonpost.com/the-trail/2008/01/09/clinton_fundraising_remains_st.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; says that Hillary has raised about 24 million bucks. That&amp;#8217;s pretty darned impressive, but let&amp;#8217;s take a moment to think about that. Nobody gives money for nothing, so the way I like to think about it is to say that she is 24 million dollars in debt. If she wins, she&amp;#8217;ll need to get that money back to those companies/people, and will probably do something to make that happen. Kind of like the current administration &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?oe=utf-8&amp;rls=com.ubuntu%3Aen-US%3Aofficial&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;um=1&amp;hl=en&amp;q=halliburton+cheney+connection&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=nw"&gt;did for Halliburton&lt;/a&gt;, except more democratic. So we have a new president that has biases on their very first day. Great. My solution to this is a very simple concept: publicly funded elections. I know it sounds expensive, but it serves two purposes. The first is that it allows politicians that are running for office to focus on their current jobs,  rather than focusing on raising money. The second is that it levels the playing field for third parties (see number 2 below) while creating elected officials without debts to companies. What a&amp;nbsp;concept!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number 2 - No Third Party&lt;/strong&gt;
This one is obvious. Does anybody vote green or independent (or other) outside of strongly democratic states? Is there a third party? No, not really, which means that it&amp;#8217;s either democrat or republican, i.e. status&amp;nbsp;quo. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number 3 - Nobody Knows Their Candidate&lt;/strong&gt;
It&amp;#8217;s a fact. There is so much hype around elections that pretty much everybody, including those who follow these things pretty closely don&amp;#8217;t know what their candidate stands for. What it comes down to for the democratic primary is, &amp;#8220;Black or woman?&amp;#8221; In the case of the republican primary it&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Military guy or mormon?&amp;#8221; That is not how the fate of the world (voting for president) should be decided, but I bet it&amp;#8217;s about what it&amp;#8217;s coming down to. I recently was shown a site called &lt;a href="http://www.glassbooth.com"&gt;glassbooth.com&lt;/a&gt;, which asks you some questions about your opinions on issues, and then tells you how to vote so you get a candidate that agrees with your opinions. Doesn&amp;#8217;t that make more sense? Can&amp;#8217;t we have that when we vote for&amp;nbsp;president? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number 4 - State Electorate System&amp;#8230;Broken.&lt;/strong&gt;
Shall we face it yet that having our vote broken up by state electorate points doesn&amp;#8217;t make much sense? Why should our votes be broken up by artificial lines in the sand? It doesn&amp;#8217;t pass the logic test if you ask me. For example, there was a recent measure in California to redistrict the state, thus allowing a more accurate split of its points. That makes sense, but why not just do away with the whole outdated system altogether? It&amp;#8217;s time, isn&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number 5 - Voter Ignorance/Impossibly Complicated Issues&lt;/strong&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ll be the first to admit that I don&amp;#8217;t know what most of the candidates stand for on an issue by issue basis (see number three above). I think I have some idea, but that&amp;#8217;s only after studying up, and I still feel kind of ignorant on much of it. Think about this squirrelly question: is a tax break good for the economy? How much of the population knows enough economics to understand this issue? Maybe one percent, and probably more like one percent of one percent. Yet, all of the population votes on the issue, and most of it votes depending on who has the greater advertising money, and thus the more convincing ads. That doesn&amp;#8217;t make a whole lot of sense, and I&amp;#8217;m not sure what to do about it. It&amp;#8217;s not a winning concept, and it can be expanded to other issues, such as stem cells, wire tapping, money for schools,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="politics"></category><category term="elections"></category></entry><entry><title>A Website that Irks My Soul, and the Internet’s Inability to Kill It</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/19/a-website-that-irks-my-soul-and-the-internets-inability-to-kill-it/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-11-19T21:15:49-08:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-11-19:posts/2007/11/19/a-website-that-irks-my-soul-and-the-internets-inability-to-kill-it/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a website a friend pointed out to me. It&amp;#8217;s called c o n s e r v o p 
e d i a, only without the spaces and with a .com at the end. It exemplifies 
so much in the world that is wrong. For example, here&amp;#8217;s the picture on the 
page entitled&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;Liberal&amp;#8221;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Liberal Brain" src="http://michaeljaylissner.com/images/Liberal_Brain_0.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correct me if I&amp;#8217;m wrong, but this is a just a bit&amp;nbsp;annoying. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&amp;#8217;t mention this to bash that site (though I hate it), 
I mention it because it exemplifies a problem of sorts with the Internet. 
The problem is this: if I want to give props to a site, 
I can do so &lt;a href="http://www.gossamergear.com"&gt;in a heartbeat by linking to it&lt;/a&gt;. A fine example of this was 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_bomb"&gt;Google Bombing&lt;/a&gt;, while it lasted. On the other hand, 
if a website blows and I feel that it is making the world a worse place, 
all I can do is put spaces in its name and hope it becomes obscure enough to
 go away (which this one is not about to&amp;nbsp;do). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagine there are some rather contentious issues regarding an internet 
where websites can be voted up and down on a grander scale than digg, 
but really, if something is evil and doing harm and disservice to the world,
 there should be a way to make it more obscure than the search engine&amp;#8217;s 
 algorithm. Similarly, if a website is doing illegal stuff, 
 we should be able to get rid of it quickly and without a lot of hassle 
 (think Internet scam&amp;nbsp;sites).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="infotech"></category></entry><entry><title>The Singularity Is Near</title><link href="http://michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/10/12/the-singularity-is-near/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-10-12T22:53:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Mike Lissner</name></author><id>tag:michaeljaylissner.com,2007-10-12:posts/2007/10/12/the-singularity-is-near/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I know what you&amp;#8217;re thinking: &amp;#8220;The Singularity - What is Mike talking about? This must be stupid.&amp;#8221; I&amp;#8217;m here to say that it might be stupid, but bear with me because I can&amp;#8217;t decide if it is, and I need to know the public&amp;nbsp;consensus. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Singularity is this theory I have been reading far too much about that there will come a time when &amp;#8220;computers transcend biology.&amp;#8221; Think about that for a moment: computers&amp;#8230;transcend&amp;#8230;biology. In other words, there will come a time when computers are so advanced that they have moved beyond the limitations of biology; beyond what we now think of as computers, and into some biocomputing&amp;nbsp;nano-thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book I&amp;#8217;m reading right now is &lt;em&gt;The Singularity is Near&lt;/em&gt; by Ray Kurzweil. It sounds like a joke, and you&amp;#8217;d think he was some two-bit writer that didn&amp;#8217;t cite his references, or that didn&amp;#8217;t know his shit, but sadly, the book has over 100 pages of references, and the man teaches at Stanford. So he&amp;#8217;s qualified to write about crazy future&amp;nbsp;ideas. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine if technological change occurred at an exponentially exponential rate (crazy, I know), and that in about 33 years - give or take - we will experience the Singularity. At that point, computers will be able to build themselves. Software will write itself, and because it is being written by software that doesn&amp;#8217;t make mistakes like ordinary humans, new versions and steps forward in technology will happen so quickly that we won&amp;#8217;t be able to keep up. It sounds crazy at first, but then you start to think about it: We have programming languages, and we have Integrated Development Environments that help us mortals to write software. Is it so crazy to think that the two might merge, and that software might write&amp;nbsp;itself? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes? &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, you&amp;#8217;re probably referring to the fact that computers don&amp;#8217;t have creative powers. This is true, but, like a child, they can learn language autonomously, and build themselves autonomously already. For example, out here in the Bay Area, we&amp;#8217;re near Google, who has just rolled out a new service called Goog-411. Basically, you call 1-800-Goog-411, and a machine will record your voice, ask you what location and business name. It will then (seemingly without fail), give you the phone number for the location, and connect you (for free). It&amp;#8217;s great, and what&amp;#8217;s more amazing is that the success of your call teaches the computer how to better help the next person. The more people call, the better it&amp;nbsp;works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we have computers that can build themselves already, and we have computers that could theoretically write themselves from the ground up. Imagine if we had computers that could analyze the news, and attempt to fix&amp;nbsp;problems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above seems plausible to me, more or less. I mean, forty years ago, we didn&amp;#8217;t even have computers. Now we have ones that can write the &lt;a href="http://www.soe.ucsc.edu/pipermail/genome/2000-July/000021.html"&gt;entire human genome on a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or if you prefer, it can do it eight or nine times on a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DVD&lt;/span&gt;.  That&amp;#8217;s all the information needed to create a human. On a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CD&lt;/span&gt;. Is it so crazy to believe that computers will be able to do what we humans can? I&amp;#8217;m not so skeptical any more. Will the timing be around 2040&amp;#8230;I think it may.&amp;nbsp;Freaky.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="singularity"></category><category term="book"></category><category term="infotech"></category></entry></feed>