<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael Jay Lissner</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/feeds/rant.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/</id><updated>2009-05-24T23:34:44+02:00</updated><entry><title>Every Now and Again, I Rant About Ipods</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/05/24/sometimes-i-rant-about-ipods/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-05-24T23:34:44+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2009-05-24:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2009/05/24/sometimes-i-rant-about-ipods/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like the title says, every now and again, I have to rant about how annoying
iPods (and by extension, Apple) are. This is one of those times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture below represents the folder hierarchy of my 20GB iPod, 
as displayed in the Ubuntu Disk Analyzer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="iPods Annoy Me" src="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/images/ipods annoy me.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, this iPod is nearly full. I filled it with a very normal 
hodge-podge of songs. Naturally, I like some artists better than others, 
and so, I have more of their songs. &lt;em&gt;The Beatles&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Zeppelin&lt;/em&gt;, for example, 
I have a lot of. &lt;em&gt;A-Ha&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Four Non Blonds&lt;/em&gt;, not so much. When this is the 
case, I'll have a folder filled with lots of songs - a big folder. If you 
look at the image above though, you'll see that my iPod is organized into 
50 equal directories, named r1 to r50.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, why would Apple do this? Why would they take perfectly organized songs
in neat and tidy folders and then split them into 50 folders with 
meaningless names? Because that makes it more of a pain in the butt to 
figure out what music is on the iPod, and in theory makes it harder to 
share the songs. For the copyright violators, this should slow them down. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the rest of the world, it's a pain, because rather than browsing our 
iPod like we would a normal music player, instead we must use iTunes, or, 
if we use Linux, reverse engineer the thing, which invariably doesn't work 
that well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple could have made a device that worked normally on all computers, 
like everybody else did, but instead they have locked us into iTunes, 
a weird directory structure, and a system designed to be as obscure as 
possible. Not cool.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ipod"></category><category term="rant"></category><category term="DRM"></category></entry><entry><title>It's OK to Advertise the Holdiays Now...</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/12/02/its-ok-to-advertise-the-holidays-now/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-12-02T08:53:23+01:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2008-12-02:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/12/02/its-ok-to-advertise-the-holidays-now/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I noticed this year that the winter holiday advertising actually came &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Halloween. I could be wrong, but didn't it used to be a faux pas to do this before Thanksgiving? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh well, this is a few days late, but I just wanted to mention that it's officially OK to roll out last year's music and crank up the commerce pressure machine.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="holidays"></category><category term="commerce"></category><category term="gripe"></category></entry><entry><title>I Just Heard About This</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/07/19/i-just-heard-about-this/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-07-19T20:22:52+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2008-07-19:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/07/19/i-just-heard-about-this/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just learned about this, but it's pretty shocking so I thought I would 
post it. Apparently a few years ago, Bush said that he uses "The Google". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observe:
&lt;object width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/MunMCO3uNdA&amp;hl=en&amp;fs=1"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/MunMCO3uNdA&amp;hl=en&amp;fs=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's pretty bad. He's the president. From this clip, 
it's pretty obvious that he doesn't use the internet. It would probably be a
useful tool for his line of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, McCain said, "Well, basically, 
&lt;strong&gt;it's a Google&lt;/strong&gt;. You just, you know, what you can find out now on the Internet. It's remarkable, you know." Emphasis mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also says, "I am a [computer] illiterate that has to rely on my wife for 
all of the assistance that I can get."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cnn.com/video/#/video/politics/2008/06/25/moos.mccain.doesnt.compute.cnn"&gt;Observe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is really, really sad. Is there &lt;strong&gt;ANY&lt;/strong&gt; job for which you 
would deliberately hire somebody that professes internet and computer illiteracy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shocking.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="politics"></category><category term="elections"></category></entry><entry><title>Lessons from the Street</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/06/23/lessons-from-the-street/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-06-23T19:29:42+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2008-06-23:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/06/23/lessons-from-the-street/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been more aware of the happenings in the street lately after one roommate had his car stolen, another had hers broken into (they took a bag of coins), and my car was front-ended a week or two ago. I've learned some valuable lessons just by watching what people are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. I have a mattress, and live in Berkeley. How do I get rid of it?&lt;/strong&gt;
Get a U-Haul. Go to Fairview St. Remove mattress from truck. Set it on the curb. Depart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. It's noon on a Sunday, and I've finished my breakfast. How do I dispose of my beer bottle?&lt;/strong&gt;
First, find a storm drain in a gutter, preferably one with a metal grate. Smash the bottle, either with your foot or the grate. Using your foot, sweep the debris into the drain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously. This is what people do on my block. I just do not get it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="berkeley"></category></entry><entry><title>Meet My Enemy</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/05/15/meet-my-enemy/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-05-15T22:26:41+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2008-05-15:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/05/15/meet-my-enemy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'd like everybody to meet my new enemy, and that of my girlfriend, 
who is now working against bottled water. Behold Fuji: traveler from 
distant seas, pillager of distant islands, waster of petroleum, 
and emptier of pockets. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No Alt" src="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/images/Fiji bottle_0.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, not only is &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/products?q=fiji+water&amp;amp;oe=utf-8&amp;amp;scoring=p"&gt;Fiji water expensive&lt;/a&gt;, but it also COMES FROM FIJI!!!! 
Think about that for a moment. Fiji is an island in the middle of the 
Pacific. Behold the planet Earth, and the island of Fiji:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=fiji&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;z=6"&gt;&lt;img alt="No alt" src="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/images/FijiMap2.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow, the water must get from there to here (it's about 5,
500 miles to the bay area). Luckily, the bottle is square so they can fit a
lot of it on a ship, but it must be bottled for weeks and months before it
arrives here. Why are we pillaging this island? It's madness.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="water"></category><category term="environment"></category></entry><entry><title>Amazon Has mp3's! I Wish I Could Download Them...</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/01/22/amazon-has-mp3s/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-01-22T19:04:40+01:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2008-01-22:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2008/01/22/amazon-has-mp3s/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It made some headlines, and is about to make more during superbowl. 
&lt;a href="http://www.news.com/8301-10784_3-9848258-7.html?tag=newsmap"&gt;Amazon 
has started selling mp3's from all four of the major record labels.&lt;/a&gt; It's a 
pretty cool revelation, so I went ahead and checked it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guess what? Linux users, you are screwed. In order to download albums from 
Amazon, you must "Get the Amazon mp3 downloader"...which is not available for 
Linux. Excuse me? Say what? I have downloaded literally hundreds upon hundreds 
of files from the Internet, and never have I needed a special tool other than 
Firefox. Why now? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon, if you're going to do something great like this, do it whole hog. 
Don't make me install junkware. After all, I'm &lt;em&gt;choosing&lt;/em&gt; to give you 
money, right? &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="copyright"></category><category term="amazon"></category><category term="rant"></category></entry><entry><title>An Important Distinction</title><link href="http://mlissner.github.io/michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/26/an-important-distinction/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-11-26T17:02:25+01:00</updated><author><name>Michael Lissner</name></author><id>tag:mlissner.github.io,2007-11-26:michaeljaylissner.com/posts/2007/11/26/an-important-distinction/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the record people:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quite:&lt;/strong&gt; I haven't &lt;strong&gt;quite&lt;/strong&gt; finished my soup. This is &lt;strong&gt;quite&lt;/strong&gt; a nice 
 restaurant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quiet:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a &lt;strong&gt;quiet&lt;/strong&gt; restaurant. I enjoy peace and &lt;strong&gt;quiet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recently looked for roommates, and we subtracted points from anybody that 
wrote in their response email the word "quite" where they meant to say "quiet." 
It was extraordinary how many applicant roommates think they are "a quite 
person".&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pedantry"></category><category term="rant"></category></entry></feed>